<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The excellent woman a sermon preached at the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Scott ... on the 16 of Decemb. 1658 / by Tho. Case ...</title>
            <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 124 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C829</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15626096</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15626096</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1183:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The excellent woman a sermon preached at the funeral of Mrs. Elizabeth Scott ... on the 16 of Decemb. 1658 / by Tho. Case ...</title>
                  <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 91, [3], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Gibs ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Several letters from divers ministers concerning the life and death of Mistresse Elizabeth Scott"--132 p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scott, ELizabeth, d. 1658.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Excellent Woman.</hi> A SERMON Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Funeral of Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Scott,</hi> Relict to <hi>Humphry Scott</hi> of <hi>Conghurſt</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> Eſq; And daughter unto Sir <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Howland</hi> Knight, late of <hi>Giles</hi> in the <hi>Fields;</hi> On the 16. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1658. By <hi>Tho. Caſe,</hi> M. A. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Student of <hi>Ch. Ch. Oxon.</hi> Now Rector of St. <hi>Giles</hi> in the <hi>Fields.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 13.7, 8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſe faith follow, confidering the end of their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, Jeſus Chriſt the ſame ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, and to day, and for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed for <hi>Robert Gibs</hi> in Chancery-lane at the ſign of the <hi>Golden Ball,</hi> near <hi>Serjeants</hi> Inn. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:2"/>
            <head>To the truly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and much honoured, The Lady <hi>Frances Howland,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict to the worthy Sir <hi>Mathew Howland</hi> late of <hi>Giles</hi> in the <hi>Fields.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not need to fear the <hi>reviving</hi> of your ſorrowes by this late ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; I finde them still
<pb facs="tcp:104249:3"/>
               <hi>freſh</hi> upon your ſpirit; and I dare not accuſe you for it: I had almoſt ſaid, you cannot be guilty of <hi>an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe</hi> in your mourning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the loſſe of <hi>ſuch a childe;</hi> A child not only of the <hi>ſevereſt obedience,</hi> but of the ſweeteſt and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt reſpect to your <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>eternal good,</hi> that moſt Mothers ever had the happineſſe to bring forth.</p>
            <p>Surely it was her pious care to pay <hi>in grace,</hi> the debt which he owed you <hi>by nature:</hi> and to compenſate her <hi>natural being</hi> received from you, with your <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:3"/>
            <p>Your Ladiſhip hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten acknowledged to myſelf, and others what a <hi>ſoul-help</hi> ſhe was to you, ever ſince God was pleaſed to call her by his grace, and to <hi>reveale his ſonne in her.</hi> Surely as ſeldome have <hi>children</hi> loſt a <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mother;</hi> ſo ſeldome did <hi>mother</hi> loſe a <hi>better childe.</hi> And as ſuch a loſſe can hardly be <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wept,</hi> ſo I am afraid our times are little guilty of ſuch a ſin. Our ſin is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that we <hi>bury</hi> our <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows</hi> together in the <hi>ſame grave</hi> with our godly, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſoul-<hi>friends,</hi> as if
<pb facs="tcp:104249:4"/>we were <hi>no loſers</hi> by their death; truly would Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians put on their <hi>mourning affections,</hi> but as long as they wear their <hi>mourning garments,</hi> for their godly dead, there were leſſe cauſe of mourning.</p>
            <p>It is true, their voice to us is that of our Lord, <hi>Weep not for me;</hi> there is no cauſe (as to themſelves) to <hi>ſorrow even as others that have no hope;</hi> Yea, <hi>but weep for your ſelves, and for your children;</hi> not for their <hi>gaines,</hi> but for your <hi>loſs,</hi> loſſe of Counſel, loſs of their quickning edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Converſe; their
<pb facs="tcp:104249:4"/>prayers, comforts, loſſe of their holy jealouſie and watchfulneſſe over us, their tender compaſſions to our ſouls. Alas, a great part of Chriſtians <hi>underſtand</hi> not their loſs, and the moſt do not lay it to heart; and ſo though they quit the <hi>ſence,</hi> yet they aggravate their miſery; while they adde <hi>ſin</hi> to their affliction; even the ſin of inſenſibleneſſe:<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.11.</note> 
               <hi>Lord when thine hand is lifted up they will not ſee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt ſmitten them, but they have not grieved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am glad therefore Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam on your behalf to finde that theſe tears are not yet
<pb facs="tcp:104249:5"/>dried up; bleſſed are thoſe mourners that prevent not the Conſolations of the holy Ghoſt; but do patiently wait till God himſelfe come to <hi>wipe off the teares from their eyes;</hi> of which this will be a comfortable pledge, if <hi>by the ſadneſſe of the countenance the heart be made better.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 7.3.</note> Which that it may be your Ladiſhips portion, as mine own, ſhall be the earneſt prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips deeply obliged, and moſt faithful ſervant in the Goſpel. <hi>The Caſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:5"/>
            <head>To the Honourable <hi>Sir Howland Roberts</hi> of <hi>Glaſſenbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent Baronet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no ſmall priviledge to be born of <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly parents; The bleſſings of the Covenant</hi> run moſt kindly in the <hi>channell of the Covenant;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:104249:6"/>there is more to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of <hi>ſuch</hi> children then <hi>others;</hi> not only as they are under the <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of their parents prayers, (<hi>Bathſheba</hi> called <hi>Solomon</hi> the <hi>ſonne of her Vowes;</hi> and <hi>Monica</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the <hi>childe</hi> of her <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>tears;</hi>) but alſo as they themſelves have a greater <hi>holdfaſt</hi> upon God, by vertue of his holy Covenant; <hi>Lord, I am thy ſervant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.16.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſonne of thy handmaid,</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> plea.</p>
            <p>What a right you may claime to Gods family by your mother, the juſt
<pb facs="tcp:104249:6"/>character here delivered of her, will ſufficiently evidence. <hi>Her example, Counſels, prayers,</hi> are a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter portion then your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers inheritance:</hi> She tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled the ſecond time with your <hi>ſpiritual birth,</hi> and was in paine till ſhe could ſee <hi>Chriſt formed in you,</hi> and the reſt of the fruit of her loynes; and that all her children <hi>by nature</hi> might be the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of God <hi>by grace;</hi> that you might be <hi>good</hi> rather then <hi>great, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable</hi> rather then <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,</hi> that ſhe might
<pb facs="tcp:104249:7"/>go out of the world with that joy of our Lord, <hi>My ſeed ſhall ſerve him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 22.30.</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall be counted to the Lord for a generation,</hi> this was the travel of her ſoul. <hi>Solomon</hi> recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Prophecy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 31.1</note> which his <hi>Mother</hi> taught him; and ſurely as by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of your pious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo by the gracious counſels and inſtructions which from the very cradle, ſhe was perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually inſtilling into your minde, ſhe being <hi>dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> the module whereof is indelibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon your heart.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:7"/>
            <p>The greatneſſe of your loſſe is not eaſie to be told; and it is not <hi>yours</hi> onely but the <hi>whole Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> ſhe was a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an indeed</hi> in all the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities</hi> which ſhe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined, and filled them all with ſingular wiſdom and fidelity. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God in taking her away in the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of her <hi>ſtrength</hi> and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity for Jeſus Chriſt; is to me very ſtupendious, and compared with the premature death of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others of the Lords <hi>choice ones,</hi> ſeemeth to intimate ſome approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:104249:8"/>judgement; <hi>The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous periſheth and man layeth it to heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1.</note> 
               <hi>and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from THE EVIL TO COME.</hi> When the corn is reaped and gathered into the barne, the bruit Cattel are turned into the field: Such a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, ſudden, and (to us) untimely death of the godly, calleth upon ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivours to ſit down, and conſider, how they may either <hi>prevent,</hi> or <hi>prepare</hi> for approaching evils; at leaſt how they may fill
<pb facs="tcp:104249:8"/>up the <hi>vacant roomes</hi> of thoſe <hi>worthies</hi> that are gone to reſt, with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter activity of grace, and a more diffuſive ſervice.</p>
            <p>As for your ſelfe (Honoured Sir) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining hopes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Fathers houſe; go on to doe <hi>worthily for God;</hi> and let the world know that your <hi>Mothers Bleſſing</hi> is not yet worne out of your familie; and that <hi>power of Religion</hi> which ſhe fought to ſtabliſh there, did <hi>not expire</hi> with
<pb facs="tcp:104249:9"/>her. Which as it is the <hi>hope,</hi> ſo it ſhall be <hi>the prayer</hi> of him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Obſervance,</hi> Tho. Caſe</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:9"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Do eaſily fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the large commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I have given to that truly Honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe memory is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in theſe papers, may incur <hi>cenſure</hi> from <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:</hi> or elſe thoſe, who though not altogether ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, were not ſo <hi>intimately acquainted</hi> with her worth and excellency; (<hi>painted</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:104249:10"/>pieces look beſt at a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> but <hi>real</hi> and <hi>living</hi> are not diſcovered but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>nearer approaches.</hi> An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore a word to avoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prejudice will not be unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs it is ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſad to obſerve how unab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> many Profeſſors are to <hi>bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>juſt commendation</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe who do <hi>excell</hi> in ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tue: I am not willing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſearch into the <hi>reaſons</hi> leſt I be thought to <hi>burde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> others with <hi>cenſure,</hi> while<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſeek to <hi>caſt it off</hi> from m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelf, I will onely ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> much, It is as unworthy, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to <hi>envy</hi> the glory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:104249:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem that are illuſtrious, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t would be to <hi>detract</hi> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem: Eſpecially when their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>minency is reported, not for the <hi>diſcouragement</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>reproach</hi> of them that are in a lower ſphere, but for their <hi>inſtruction,</hi> and to provoke to imitation. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould rather chear us to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart to ſee the <hi>beames</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lords grace breaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut with ſo much <hi>glory</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Giver,</hi> and that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s glorified <hi>by others,</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>our ſelves;</hi> and that while we are at the <hi>bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> of the <hi>hill,</hi> others get <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earer to the <hi>top</hi> &amp; <hi>height</hi> of Chriſtian perfection.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:11"/>
            <p>My <hi>Apology</hi> is this; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in this report I have <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded</hi> the bounds of trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and modeſty, <hi>bear witneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to the exceſſe; but if I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken the <hi>truth,</hi> why am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſmitten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the truth of wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have ſpoken, let the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed Teſtimonies of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>godly Divines,</hi> with other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique witneſſes <hi>bear re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord:</hi> as alſo thoſe many others that might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced both in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, who had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be privy and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to her <hi>walk</hi> and <hi>courſe</hi> I may truly ſay <hi>ſhe had a
<pb facs="tcp:104249:11"/>good report of all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Joh. 12.</note> 
               <hi>and of the truth it ſelfe.</hi> Now whether in this <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> given of this worthy Christian, I have been acted by a <hi>ſpirit of flattery,</hi> or a deſire <hi>to do good;</hi> Yea, whither ſo much to <hi>honour</hi> the <hi>dead,</hi> as to provoke the living to an holy emulation of like <hi>ſtrictneſſe,</hi> and <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Converſation,</hi> the Searcher of hearts knoweth, <hi>who will both bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the Counſels of the hearts; and then ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man have the praiſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:12"/>
            <p>Reader, how much more honour and comfort will it be in that day to be a <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower</hi> of what thou readeſt then a <hi>Judge,</hi> I leave to thine own conſcience to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine: The Lord give thee <hi>to profit</hi> by this, and other the inſtances of his <hi>grace,</hi> which is the prayer of him, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the ſervice of the Goſpel. <hi>Tho. Caſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104249:12"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PROVERBS 31.29.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many Daughters have done vertuouſly, but thou excellest them all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He nine firſt Verſes of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contain a notable <hi>Modell</hi> of Inſtructions which <hi>Solomons Mother</hi> taught him; calculated moſt properly for his uſe and direction as he was a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104249:13"/>
            <p>It is called a <hi>Propheſie,</hi> under which notion <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel</hi> and <hi>Inſtruction</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignified (not in the Old-Teſtament onely, but alſo in the New) the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall occaſion whereof was, becauſe the Office of the Prophets was to <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>inſtruct</hi> the people, as well as to <hi>foretell</hi> and <hi>reveal</hi> things to <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This fatter part of the Chapter from the tenth verſe to the end, containe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a moſt elegant deſcriptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of an <hi>excellent woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom this Characte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is to be aſcribed, admits o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> varions thoughts amongſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Interpreters.</p>
            <p>The Papiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attribute i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the <hi>Virgin Mary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104249:13"/>to <hi>the Church,</hi> the Spouſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Rabbi <hi>Solomon</hi> applieth it to the <hi>Old Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (after him) <hi>Lyra</hi> to the whole <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all theſe are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wide, but wilde conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</p>
            <p>Some with more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ribe it to <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba, Solomons</hi> Mother; as pen'd and compoſed by <hi>Solomon</hi> as an Encomium or Panegyrick of her Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies; which he ded<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cates unto her by way of a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatory acknowledgement of her ſingular piety in theſe Motherly inſtructions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in the former part of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>But laſtly, others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that the whole deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104249:14"/>to be but the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an excelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t woman</hi> at large, and not particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly applyed to any ſingle perſon, but as it were a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Draught</hi> or <hi>Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> by which we may know an excellent woman, a <hi>Wife</hi> indeed, when we ſee her.</p>
            <p>And it is conceived that this deſcription is a continued part of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie which <hi>Bathſheba</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated unto <hi>Solomon,</hi> and was ſpecially intended to be his <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Standard</hi> in the choice of a Wife; the ſpecial ſtudy and care of a pious Mother, as we ſee in <hi>Rebecca</hi> towards <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 29.46. And to this conjecture I doe rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:104249:14"/>
            <p>In this deſcription, the eighthteenth precedent verſes contain the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vertues and praiſes of this excellent Woman, my Text is the <hi>ſumma totalis,</hi> the Compendium and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronis of the whole <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> wherewith ſhe is <hi>Crowned</hi> (as it were) in the face of Heaven and Earth, God and Angels and Men; <hi>Many Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have done vertuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have done <hi>vertuouſly,</hi>] the Original Word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth properly to <hi>bring forth children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l <hi>from</hi> Chul dolore, eviti.</note> with <hi>ſorrow</hi> and hard <hi>labour:</hi> hence alſo it ſometimes ſignifieth <hi>vertue,</hi> ſometimes <hi>riches:</hi> becauſe neither is ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attained and proſecuted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104249:15"/>without much induſtry and activity;<note place="margin">Gnaſhu Chaijl fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerunivir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem.</note> the phraſe here uſed (to the letter) is to be tranſlated <hi>have done vertue;</hi> or performed <hi>worthy</hi> things; they have acted <hi>ſtrenuouſly</hi> which ſeems to approve our tranſlation, as that which is moſt proper. <hi>They have done vertuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many Daughters</hi>] Daughters, here is taken <hi>more Hebraico</hi> for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; as men are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sons,</hi> ſo women are called <hi>Daughters,</hi> Cant 3.5.</p>
            <p>But how doth this p u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of good Women (<hi>many Daughters</hi> have done <hi>vertuouſly</hi>) agree with that complaint of <hi>Solomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.28.</note> 
               <hi>one man amongſt a thouſand have I found, but a Woman
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104249:15"/>amongſt all theſe have I not found?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſalve the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty thus; <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks in refference to his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; He</hi> had not found one good Woman indeed amongſt a thouſand, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to his former ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual converſe with women;) He had a thouſand Wives and Concubines, all the <hi>Daughters of ſtrange pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Nations:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was no wonder he could not finde <hi>one good</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all, they all proved <hi>ſnares</hi> to him <hi>to turn away his heart from the Lord unto Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 11.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe words are <hi>Bathſhebas</hi> words in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>her own</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who by converſing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104249:16"/>with a better ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men then her Sonne did; found not onely <hi>one,</hi> but <hi>many good ones</hi> of that ſex, <hi>many Daughters have done vertuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but even ſhe makes a very great difficulty alſo of finding <hi>one;</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> Verſe 10. <hi>Who can finde a vertuous woman, for her price is far above Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies:</hi> the queſtion ſeemes to imply a good woman to be a rare jewel, and hardly to be found.</p>
            <p>But the Anſwer (to both theſe Objections) is,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> that neither the meaning of <hi>Solomon</hi> nor his <hi>Mother</hi> is to condemn <hi>one ſex</hi> more then the other, But both are to be underſtood <hi>compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> (and alas it holds too true in both Sexes) the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104249:16"/>number of the truly good is but very ſmall and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiderable, compared with the <hi>vile</hi> &amp; <hi>vitious,</hi> whether of men or women. The bad are like <hi>pebble ſtones</hi> upon the Sea ſhore, you cannot ſtir a foot but ye ſtumble upon them, but the good are like <hi>precious ſtones, Rubies,</hi> and <hi>Diamonds</hi> of great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and rarely to be found; the <hi>Merchant</hi> that will find them muſt <hi>travell far</hi> for them: To which ſad truth the Apoſtle beareth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Not many wiſe, nor many mighty, not many noble, &amp;c.</hi> Bleſſed be God he doth not ſay <hi>no any wiſe, not any migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> ſome there be which though but <hi>a little flock,</hi> compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the Droves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104249:17"/>and Herds which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel carrieth head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong into the Sea of perdition; yet conſidered in themſelve they are not a contempt ible number; <hi>Revel.</hi> 7. from the 4th verſe to the 8 9, 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h.</p>
            <p>But then again, amongſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe many, there is here and there a <hi>rare</hi> one to be found, <hi>a pearle of great price, many</hi> good; and ſome <hi>one excellent</hi> a <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> a <hi>None-ſuch</hi> in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>place</hi> and <hi>age,</hi> To whom it may be ſaid, <hi>Thou excelleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words thus opened and cleared, will affords u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Obſer. <hi>All the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Crurch are not of the ſame preciouſneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104249:17"/>there be ſeverall ſizes of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God takes notice of the leaſt grace and goodneſs that is in any:</hi> grace in what degree ſoever it is, (if it betrue) God will not overlook it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The great honour and praiſe of a Chriſtian, is to be excellent in their generations:</hi> Or, <hi>Excellency in grace and goodneſs, is that which is of great price in the ſight of God:</hi> God doth ſet a ſpecial note of approbation upon it, <hi>thou excelleſt them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Members of the Church are not of the ſame ſize in grace.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In this firmament of the Church, it is as in the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavens; <hi>one Star differeth from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in glory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.41.</note> all Stars are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104249:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>not of the ſame light and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; ſome there be of the <hi>firſt,</hi> ſome of the <hi>ſecond</hi> magnitude; others that are of a common dimenſion and influence: <hi>ſo is the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 42.</note> 
               <hi>this</hi> here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> hereafter in <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Houſhold of Faith</hi> all the <hi>Members</hi> be not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be ſome <hi>Babe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Christ,</hi> Babes i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and Babe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>grace,</hi> weake an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tender Chriſtans, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have little more the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the very <hi>being</hi> of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall life in them,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.12, 13, 14.</note> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough to denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them <hi>Saints</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some there be <hi>youn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104249:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>men;</hi> ſtrong act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſtrong to <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Divel</hi> in all his temptations, and active in their generations, able to doe <hi>much work</hi> for Jeſus Chriſt and the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And then there be <hi>Fathers</hi> in the Church, Chriſtians of <hi>much experience</hi> in the <hi>myſtery of the Kingdom of God:</hi> Chriſtians of <hi>great acquaintance with God,</hi> and communion with God who can ſay with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.3</note> 
               <hi>Truly our Communion is with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt the Worthies of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vid,</hi> all did not attain the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fame and enown with the <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt three</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104249:19"/>
            <p>Well; Let not the <hi>weake Chriſtian envy</hi> the <hi>ſtrong,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> nor the <hi>ſtrong deſpiſe</hi> the <hi>weake;</hi> but ſee God and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire God in the ſeverall gifts and graces of his Spirit. So it muſt be in the Church of God.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly Obſerve; <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>God takes notice of the leaſt good that is in any:</hi> Grace in what ever degree (if it be true) is not rejected by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. The <hi>bruiſed Reed he will not breake, and the ſmonking Flax he will not quen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h;</hi> what is weaker then a <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſed reed;</hi> behold while it was <hi>whole,</hi> it was fit for little ſervice; but when it is <hi>bruiſed</hi> it is good for <hi>nothing:</hi> you cannot make a pin of it to hang a veſſel on: what is more uſeleſs then <hi>ſmoaking
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104249:19"/>flax;</hi> ſinged and ſcorched with the fire, and ready to breake out into a flame; ye cannot make a thread of it fit for any work. Yet that grace which in the ſence and feeling of a Chriſtian, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that is <hi>poore in ſpirit,</hi> is of no more conſideration then ſuch <hi>ſmoaking flax,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>bruiſed reed;</hi> behold Jeſus Chriſt will be ſo farre from <hi>quenching</hi> of the one, and <hi>breaking</hi> the other, that he will bring it forth into victory; <hi>weake grace</hi> ſhall at length get the conqueſt of <hi>ſtrong corruption;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is very obſervable in the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> Rev. 2. and 3. Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. there's not any thing that was good in any of them, but Jeſus Chriſt takes ſpecial notice of it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104249:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I know thy labour and thy patience;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. chap. 2.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and thou canſt not bear with them which are evil, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Smy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na;</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 9.</note> 
               <hi>I know thy works and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and poverty, but thou art rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pergamus, <note place="margin">verſe 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt faſt my Name, and haſt not denyed my Faith, though thou dwelleſt where Satan hath his ſeate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thyatyra, <note place="margin">verſe 19.</note> 
               <hi>Thy works and charity, and ſervice, and faith, and patience, and</hi> (againe) <hi>thy works,</hi> I and thy <hi>laſt to be more then the firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sardis, hath a <hi>few Names,</hi> and Philadelphia a <hi>little ſtrength,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 3.4. verſe 8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was not the leaſt good in any of the Churches, though intermixt with much
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104249:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in, and corruption, but it is taken notice of, and record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Regiſter of Gods remembrance, &amp; is mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their honour &amp; praiſe; only there was <hi>proud conceited Laodicea</hi> that had nothing but an <hi>high oopinion</hi> of her ſelf,<note place="margin">ver. 16.</note> and ſhe ſtands with a <hi>brand</hi> upon her <hi>forehead,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a <hi>Crown</hi> upon her <hi>head; Luke-warm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In wicked <hi>Jeroboams</hi> fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there was but one poore childe, that <hi>had ſome good in him,</hi> and that but very little, yet that is taken notice of, and an <hi>aſteriſm</hi> ſet upon it; <hi>In him was found ſome good thing toward the Lord God of Iſrael. Therefore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Daughters that had done vertuouſly are <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record,</hi> though they came
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104249:21"/>not up to the <hi>character</hi> of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>excellent woman,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As all that helped to <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the wall of Jeruſale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had not a like ſhare in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work, yet all their <hi>nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> are upon the <hi>file,</hi> their <hi>labo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of love</hi> is regiſtred and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to ſucceeding gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>The Ground or Reaſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this Obſervation is this,<note place="margin">Ground.</note> 
               <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Becauſe true grace thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> never ſo ſmall, is the<note n="a" place="margin"> Phil. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of God;</hi> yea, the<note n="b" place="margin"> Eph. 4.24.</note> 
               <hi>Image, God;</hi> a<note n="c" place="margin"> 2 Pet. 1.4.</note> beam of the <hi>Divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nature:</hi> and God will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>deſpiſe the work of his o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hands: God will own eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one that is called by his Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> why? for <hi>I have created hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for my glory, I have form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him, yea I have made him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God knows how to diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh<note place="margin">Iſa 43.7.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:104249:21"/>between the <hi>Gold</hi> and the <hi>droſs;</hi> between <hi>a want</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>a want</hi> in <hi>grace:</hi> between <hi>ſincerity</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uption</hi> in his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>childe</hi> and a <hi>baſtard:</hi> And he will not throw the heap of corn into the fire, becauſe there is much <hi>chaff</hi> in it; he will not <hi>reprobate</hi> the <hi>gold</hi> becauſe there is <hi>droſs</hi> mixt with it:<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.17, 18.</note> nor <hi>diſinherit</hi> the <hi>childe</hi> becauſe a <hi>weake childe: froward Ephraim,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a <hi>childe,</hi> God will <hi>heal him, and lead him, and reſtore comforts to him, and to his mourners.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>It may ſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To encourage weake Chriſtians, ſay not in thy heart <hi>I have no grace,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104249:22"/>
                  <hi>thou findeſt much corruptio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> God doth not ſay ſo. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> heavenly Father can diſcov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>ſpark</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> in a <hi>ſea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> corruption,</hi> Chriſtians mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> learn to diſtinguiſh betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>having</hi> of corruption<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the <hi>allowing</hi> of corru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, between a <hi>little grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and being <hi>contented</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> little grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may ſerve to <hi>Cauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> us <hi>againſt deſpiſing of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weaker brethren.</hi> He is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſpirit and diſpoſitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our heavely Father, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can deſpiſe one of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>little ones,</hi> a little faith, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a little ſtrength; ſome goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing towards the Lord, Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>takes notice</hi> of, and Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>owns;</hi> ſo ſhould we; if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> will be the Children of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heavenly Father. <hi>Him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:104249:22"/>weeke in faith receive,</hi> onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot <hi>to doubtfull diſputations;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">So is the Rule, Ro. 14.1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhould own the weakeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hriſtians, to encourage and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elp their graces, but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perplex them with unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able diſputes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may ſerve as an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouragement to all to be <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od;</hi> to labour <hi>to get grace,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho would not ſerve ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, as will own the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood that is in his children? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at knows how to pardon <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reat ſins,</hi> and to accept of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> little grace</hi> where there is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cerity?</hi> Bring into God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat thou haſt, thy <hi>mite</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall be accepted, if it be all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou haſt.<note place="margin">Farre li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabo perſius</note> 
                  <hi>A paire of Turtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ves</hi> will be accepted on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ods Altar, as well as coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Sacrifices; where the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rificers ability will extend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104249:23"/>no higher. <hi>But curſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the deceiver which hath in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Flock a Male,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſacrifice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the Lord a co rupt thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A man is accepted with Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> according to what he hath.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> according to what he hath no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Onely <hi>let not this make y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> idle,</hi> to be <hi>content</hi> with a litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grace, <hi>becauſe God will acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a little:</hi> argueth <hi>no grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all:</hi> know thus much I b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeech you, that though Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will <hi>own</hi> the <hi>weak</hi> Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet he delights in the <hi>exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent;</hi> which brings me upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the third and main Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which I intend to handle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The great honour a d'prai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of a Chriſtian i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be excelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in goodneſs and grace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Excellent Saints are Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take a few Demonſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104249:23"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The word of Command;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dem.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Precepts and Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons of Scripture run upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſtrain, <hi>walk before me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd be thou perfect</hi> ſaid God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Ab aham: Abraham</hi> muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot take up with any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hort of <hi>perfection.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat you may not think that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as a <hi>ſpecial inſtance</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll are not bound to follow, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Evangelical Rule which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oncerns all Chriſtians, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peaks in the very ſame Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age, <hi>Be ye perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. ult.</note> ye with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion of higheſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, <hi>as your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is perfect.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15</note> 
                  <hi>As he that hath called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, for it is written, be ye ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, for I the Lord your God am holy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſerve, Chriſtians muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104249:24"/>make God the <hi>pattern</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their holineſs, and the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of their holineſs; Holy <hi>as</hi> he is holy, there's our <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern;</hi> holy <hi>becauſe</hi> he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ther's our <hi>motive;</hi> They muſt content themſelves with no <hi>meaſure</hi> or <hi>degree</hi> of holineſs, but <hi>forgetting the things that are behinde, preſſe ſtill after further degrees</hi> of <hi>conformitie</hi> unto God. Theſe be not onely Evangelicall <hi>Counſels</hi> (as the Papiſts ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly teach, that ſo upon this <hi>foundation</hi> they may build their Superſtructure of <hi>merit</hi> and <hi>works of ſupererro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi>) but they be Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical <hi>precepts</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> enjoyned upon the great <hi>prerogative</hi> of divine <hi>filiation;</hi> and indeed <hi>flowing from it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5.45.</note> 
                  <hi>that you may be the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104249:24"/>children of your heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> there is no boaſting of <hi>divine Son-ſhip,</hi> without <hi>conformity</hi> unto the <hi>divine nature:</hi> not that this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of our <hi>Son-ſhip,</hi> but the <hi>evidence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tunc dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſaepe aliquid eſſe quum eſſe intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>Beza</hi> in loc.</note> that <hi>you may be, i. e.</hi> that you may be <hi>known</hi> to be <hi>the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of your Father which is in Heaven:</hi> According to this tenor, run all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Goſpel, <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1</note> 
                  <hi>proving what that good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi> and <hi>derfect</hi> will of God is. <hi>Be perfect,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 12.1, 2</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11. Phil. 1.10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>be of good comfort, ſincere without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, filled with the fruits of righteouſneſs. Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">chap. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, lovely, of good
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104249:25"/>report; if any vertue, if any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Brethren, the purity of <hi>Scripture Rule,</hi> and the perfection of <hi>Scripture Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> are the two impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Arguments and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of the <hi>Div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Scripture,</hi> and the truth of Chriſtian Religion againſt all other Religions in the world. Behold, the Rule is an <hi>Excellent Rule</hi> which God hath chalked out to his Saints to walk by: cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for nothing ſhort of <hi>perfection,</hi> in their aimes and utmoſt contention! <hi>How perfect is the Law of God!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7. 2. <hi>Dem.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Demonſtration, <hi>ſuch God commends,</hi> and of ſuch onely <hi>God boaſts</hi> in Scripture, <hi>haſt thou not conſidered my ſervant Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 1.8.</note> ſaid God to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104249:25"/>Satan, <hi>there is none like him upon the face of the Earth, a perfect and an upright man! &amp;c.</hi> I know <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Abraham my friend:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.19. 1 Sam. 13.14. 2 Cor. 10.18.</note> And <hi>David, a man after mine own heart. Not he that man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth, but he that God commendeth is approved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <note place="margin">3. <hi>Dem.</hi>
                  </note> theſe Excellent ones God ſets forth as <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> and <hi>Exemplars</hi> for <hi>others imitation: Be ye fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of me as I am of Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> they be Saint <hi>Pauls words,</hi> but Gods <hi>command;</hi> whoſe <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> and <hi>Secretary</hi> the Apoſtle was; and it is the very ſame which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned unto all the <hi>followers of the Lamb,</hi> that they <hi>ſhould be followers of the Excellent ones,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.12</note> 
                  <hi>who through faith and patience inherit the promiſes.</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:104249:26"/>Not onely be ye followers of God as dear Children,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.1.</note> But, Be ye followers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m that excell in vertue,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.7</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe faith follow, conſidering the end of their converſation, Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> Yet this muſt be ſtill with the Apoſtles li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation; <hi>as they are of Chriſt,</hi> we muſt not follow the Saints further then as they follow Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly and laſtly, For the moſt <hi>excellent Saints</hi> is reſerved the moſt <hi>excellent glory.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4. <hi>Dem.</hi>
                  </note> According to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>grace</hi> here, ſhall be the degree of <hi>glory</hi> hereafter: <hi>As one Star differeth from another in glory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.41.42.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo alſo is the reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the further enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and clearing of this Doctrine I ſhall briefly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104249:26"/>one Querie, and ſo paſſe over to the Uſes of the Point. It is this.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent?</hi> or, <hi>wherein</hi> doth the <hi>excellencie</hi> of a <hi>Saint</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Wherein conſiſts the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of a Chriſtian.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Excellency con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in theſe three qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To be <hi>univerſally good.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. To be <hi>eminently good.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. To be <hi>perſeveringly good.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1. Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally heart-good, and life-good.</note> 1. To be <hi>univerſally good:</hi> this <hi>is excellent indeed,</hi> when a Chriſtian is good <hi>all over:</hi> good <hi>quite through:</hi> good <hi>within,</hi> and good <hi>without.</hi> When a man or woman is a good <hi>Firſt Table</hi> Chriſtian: and a good <hi>Second Table</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>holy</hi> towards <hi>God, righteous,</hi> meek, <hi>merciful</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>man.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104249:27"/>
               <p>They be <hi>excellent ones,</hi> that are good in <hi>both</hi> their <hi>callings:</hi> good in their <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> callings as <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> good in their <hi>particular</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings as <hi>men:</hi> good on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and good all the <hi>weeke</hi> long. Good as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,</hi> good as <hi>Miniſters,</hi> good in whatſoever <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Profeſſion</hi> God hath fixt them in amongſt men.</p>
               <p>Good in all their <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> good as <hi>Husbands,</hi> good as <hi>Wives:</hi> good as <hi>Parents,</hi> good as <hi>Children,</hi> good as <hi>Maſters,</hi> good as <hi>Servants,</hi> good as <hi>Kindred,</hi> good as <hi>Neighbours.</hi> Time will not permit exemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ification of theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe they be <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> who are good <hi>every where:</hi> good at <hi>home,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104249:27"/>good <hi>abroad,</hi> good in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,</hi> and good <hi>alone:</hi> good in <hi>good</hi> company, and good in <hi>bad:</hi> good with <hi>Saints,</hi> and good with <hi>ſinners:</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with them, as a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> among the <hi>ſick,</hi> not as a <hi>companion</hi> with them that are <hi>well:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Having no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them rather, <hi>Ep. 5.11.</hi>
                  </note> good in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> and good in the <hi>Cloſet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He or ſhe is excellent that is good in <hi>every ſtate,</hi> and <hi>in every temper:</hi> good when <hi>rich,</hi> and good when <hi>poore,</hi> good when <hi>ſick,</hi> and good when <hi>well,</hi> good in <hi>priſon,</hi> and good at <hi>libertie,</hi> good when <hi>ſad,</hi> and good when <hi>merry,</hi> good in <hi>holy duties,</hi> and good in <hi>civil Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold, <hi>this is to be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent;</hi> That is an excellent Chriſtian indeed that walks
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104249:28"/>
                  <hi>uniformly;</hi> every <hi>where,</hi> and in every <hi>thing like himſelf:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atus.</note> good when <hi>men ſee him,</hi> and good when <hi>none</hi> but <hi>God</hi> ſees him; Many of theſe <hi>qualifications</hi> we find in this deſcription and character, (here) of a <hi>good</hi> woman; ſhe is a good <hi>Wife,</hi> a good <hi>Mother,</hi> a good <hi>Widow:</hi> and that is <hi>her excellency,</hi> which we ſhall have occaſion to touch hereafter.</p>
               <p>This was the <hi>excellencie</hi> of <hi>Zechariah</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 1.6.</note> they <hi>were both righteoas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, walking in all the Commandements and Statutes of the Lord blameleſs,</hi> i. e. <hi>in all the duties of the Moral and Ceremonial Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. In emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency.</note> Secondly, The excellency of a Chriſtian conſiſts in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>eminently good, exemplari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104249:28"/>good:</hi> To be <hi>followers</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> as 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6. this is good: But to be <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples to all that believe</hi> (as verſe 7.) this is excellent.</p>
               <p>To be <hi>good</hi> is profitable <hi>unto our ſelves:</hi> but to be <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently exemplarily</hi> good, is profitable to <hi>others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He or ſhe that is <hi>really good,</hi> ſhall ſave <hi>himſelf,</hi> but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is <hi>rarely</hi> good ſhall <hi>ſave others</hi> alſo.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Their light doth ſo ſhine before men, that they ſee their good works, and glorifie their Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> this is excellent.</p>
               <p>It is a Chriſtians <hi>excellency</hi> not to ſet himſelf any <hi>bounds</hi> in <hi>holineſſe;</hi> not to content himſelf with any <hi>meaſure</hi> or <hi>degree</hi> of grace: but with the Apoſtle, to <hi>forget the things that are behinde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104249:29"/>reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before, to preſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the mark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which is the worldly mans <hi>ſhame,</hi> is the Chriſtians <hi>glory, never to have enough, what SING<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAR thing do ye doe?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.47. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Queſtion; what doe you <hi>more then others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a Chriſtians glory to be ſingular! the world hates ſingularity, but God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3. In per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>everance.</note> Thirdly, A Chriſtians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency conſiſts in being <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveringly good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye did run well;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 5.7.</note> is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of a Chriſtian, and of his profeſſion; perſeverance is the glory of both. It is the glory of a Chriſtian when <hi>their goodneſs</hi> is not as the <hi>morning cloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſ. 6.4.</note> and as the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104249:29"/>
                  <hi>early dew,</hi> that quickly paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away, but as the <hi>morning light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 4.18. Rev. 2.19.</note> which <hi>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth clearer and clearer to the perfect day.</hi> It was the ſhame of <hi>Epheſus</hi> that ſhe had loſt her <hi>firſt Love,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> but the glory of <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> that her <hi>laſt works</hi> were <hi>more</hi> then the <hi>firſt.</hi> The Trees of God bring forth more fruit in their <hi>old age,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 92.14.</note> they are <hi>fat</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing,</hi> when others <hi>wither</hi> and <hi>dye,</hi> they retain their verdure, and are <hi>full of ſap:</hi> this is the <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency</hi> of a Chriſtian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe. Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> And it may ſerve,</p>
               <p>Firſt, By way of <hi>Trial</hi> in <hi>Self-examina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion;</hi> are you ſuch Chriſtians?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Are ye <hi>univerſal</hi> in
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:104249:30"/>Lord more <hi>faith,</hi> and mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>love,</hi> and more <hi>holineſſe,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> more <hi>meekneſſe</hi> of <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irit,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more zeal,<note place="margin">Si dixti ſuffieit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſti Aug.</note> and more Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>every grace: when every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſay you have enough ye hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nothing: ye are nothing;</hi> ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from <hi>excelent</hi> that ye are not <hi>reall</hi> but a meer Lukewarme <hi>Laodicean,</hi> that ſaith, <hi>I am rich and increaſed with goods, and have need of nothing;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and knoweſt not that thou art wretched and miſerable, and poor, and blind, and naked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Are yee <hi>perſevering Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ians?</hi> Are your <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irits</hi> ſtedfaſt with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od? Are your <hi>judgements ſabliſhed</hi> in the truth? Are your <hi>hearts</hi> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in grace? doe yee <hi>keep cloſe</hi> to the good old Principles which you have ſuckt in from the breaſts of the Goſpell? &amp;c. doe ye
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104249:30"/>
                  <hi>proceed</hi> in the way that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led holy? Are <hi>ye ſtedfaſt and In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oveable alwayes aboun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the work of the Lord?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Alas brethren, if this be to be excellent, where ſhall we find an Excellent Man, or an excellent woeman? as the 10. verſe complaines <hi>who can find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertuous woman?</hi> where ſhall we finde this exccel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent daughter?</p>
               <p>Solomon or his Mother (in this Chap.) did find her,<note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> at leſt <hi>in the Character.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I can point you to her <hi>in perſon.</hi> Amongſt others &amp; before many in whom this Character (here) was ever <hi>examplified</hi> ſince <hi>Solomons</hi> time, namely in this truly <hi>Honorable Chriſtian whoſe funerals we this day celebrate</hi> M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
                  <hi>ELISABETH
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104249:31"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:104249:31"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:104249:32"/>SCOTT.</hi> Uupon whoſe <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument</hi> (where ever it ſhall ſtand) to her immortall fame and glory, may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be inſcribed This Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Many daughter have don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vertuouſly BUT THOU EXCELLEST THEM ALL.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doubtleſſe ſhe was <hi>an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelent Chriſtian,</hi> a Chriſtian of an <hi>incomparable ſpirit and complexion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe 3 <hi>ingredients</hi> of <hi>excellencie</hi> were viſible in her to the eyes of all the behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, eſpecially, ſuch who had the happineſſe of more intimate Converſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with her.</p>
               <p>She was
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vniverſally</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eminently</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Perſeveringly</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> good</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:104249:32"/>
               <p>She was <hi>Univerſally</hi> good: with that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the Goſpell <hi>ſhe walked in all the comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ements and ſtatutes of God blameleſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">inopem me c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pia fecit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thardly know where to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, leſs</hi> how to make an <hi>end</hi> of very much that I could ſay of her I will confine my ſelfe to theſe 10. <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt ſhe was a moſt <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Knowldg</hi>
                  </note> ſhe had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to an high degree of <hi>proficiency</hi> in the <hi>School of Chriſt:</hi> ſhe was as emmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently verſt in the <hi>methods of Grace and the Miſtery</hi> of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, able to ſpeak as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and pertinently to any piece of an inward pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall Chriſtian as any of her Sex and ſtanding in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ever I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104249:33"/>to be acquainte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with.</p>
               <p>When I firſt ſet upon <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament-Reformation,</hi> in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> place ſhe was the <hi>firſt</hi> in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Congregation that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the countenancing and incouraging of that wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at which time ſhe gave the moſt ſingular account of the <hi>work of grace,</hi> and <hi>confeſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of her faith</hi> that I have hard; to the very high ſatisfaction and admiration of ſuch as were preſent.<note place="margin">Wiſdome.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Scientia, is an habit of principles in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, a right improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples unto practiſe.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. And her knowledge was not only <hi>notional</hi> ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the Brain, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with moſt of the profeſſors of this age pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but <hi>her knowledge was joyned with wiſdome and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> whereby ſhe brought down all her principles into
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104249:33"/>
                  <hi>practiſe</hi> and turned every <hi>DOCTRINE</hi> into <hi>VSE;</hi> what light there was in her <hi>judgement,</hi> warned down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her <hi>heart,</hi> beamed out moſt gloriouſly in her <hi>life</hi> &amp; <hi>converſation.</hi> She was a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Chriſtian; and indeed her <hi>knowledge</hi> was the <hi>fruit</hi> of her <hi>obedience;</hi> according to the tenour of that bleſſed promiſe of our Saviour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man will doe Gods will, he ſhall know his Dotrine.</hi> A ſtrange Methode: In na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>knowledg</hi> precedes <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> in Grace <hi>action</hi> precedes <hi>knowledge:</hi> where there is an <hi>obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ientiall diſpoſition,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge flowes in a pace, they that doe Gods will that they may know it, and Labour to know Gods will that they
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104249:34"/>may doe it, are the <hi>thriving Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So it was with this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent woman</hi> Her <hi>knowledg</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ran paral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, and did mutually transfuſe vigour and vivacitie one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Notwithſtanding the greatneſſe of her knowledge <hi>She was of Singular humility</hi> Her knowledg did <hi>not puff her up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Humility.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 8.1.</note> her <hi>head</hi> was not ſo <hi>high</hi> but her <hi>heart</hi> lay as <hi>low;</hi> She was as mean in her own eyes as ſhe was honorable in the eyes of ſtanders by. She was a Chriſtian of infinite worth but She knew it not. <hi>Proud profeſſors</hi> doe not uſually ſpeak more <hi>contemptuouſly</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> then <hi>ſhe</hi> would doe of <hi>her ſelfe:</hi> ſhe was of Iobs Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104249:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though She were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhe would not know her owne ſoul; ſhe did deſpiſe her ſelfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.21.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this humility of hers was the Nurſe to all her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces;<note place="margin">Humilitas con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſrva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Bern.</note> faith is the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> humilitie the <hi>nurſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. She was a woman of a <hi>Meek an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quiet ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Meekneſs</note> which rendered her very <hi>beautifull</hi> in the eyes of <hi>God and man</hi> She could not <hi>provoke any;</hi> nor eaſily be <hi>provoked by any.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She had much of the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> which is <hi>from above</hi> which is <hi>firſt pure then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, gentle, and eaſie to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was moſt fearfull to <hi>give offence,</hi> but moſt free to <hi>forgive it:</hi> the reaſon was evident; God had forgiven
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104249:35"/>her <hi>thouſands</hi> of <hi>talents,</hi> and therefore ſhe thought it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> much to forgive <hi>a few pence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. She was a <hi>Mercifull Chriſtian;</hi> full of bowells: the Love of Chriſt both active and paſſive (<hi>i.e. Chriſts lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to her,<note place="margin">Mercy</note> and <hi>her love</hi> to Chriſt) had melted her all into Compaſſion, Compaſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the <hi>Bodies</hi> of poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Compaſſion to ſouls,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 29.13.</note> Compaſſion to the Outward man, and compaſſion to the inward. Compaſſion to the outward man: <hi>The bleſſing of him that was ready to periſh came upon her, &amp; ſhe cauſed the widows heart to ſing for joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She might ſay with Iob (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine) <hi>If I have ſeen any pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for want of cloathing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 31.19.</note> 
                  <hi>or any poore without covering &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:104249:35"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Penſioners in</hi> Ken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Conghurſt Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt, Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook, London, Giles <hi>in the fields.</hi> Miniſters.</note> Great was the number of <hi>Penſioners</hi> to whom ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owed <hi>weekly ſumms</hi> in the <hi>Country,</hi> and in the <hi>Citie,</hi> who now lie down in ſorrow, and mingle their drink with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir tears.</p>
               <p>Many precious godly <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters,</hi> whoſe ſubſiſtence was <hi>ſcantie,</hi> and meane; did ſhe ſupport and encourage with <hi>yearly ſtipends,</hi> whoſe names I could relate, were I not reſtraind.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">poor Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> 
                  <hi>She</hi> was a liberal contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buter to the maintaining of <hi>poore Scholars</hi> at the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, witneſs that <hi>ſubſcription</hi> for <hi>Kent,</hi> and divers other, to my knowledge.</p>
               <p>Oh what ſad lamentations and tears will it occaſion in many places, when it ſhall be ſadly reported
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104249:36"/>abroad, Mrs. <hi>SCOT IS DEAD!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>publique Collections</hi> for the <hi>Churches abroad,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">10. l. <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edmond.</hi>
                  </note> and to Calamitous <hi>places</hi> and <hi>perſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at home, how open and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral was her hand?</p>
               <p>Beſides, upon all the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent occaſions (which were not rare amongſt us) her charity was never ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> never deſired her contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution to any work of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but <hi>ſhe gave,</hi> and gave <hi>liberally;</hi> yea it was enough but to <hi>hint</hi> a conſiderable work of <hi>piety</hi> or <hi>charity;</hi> Yea ſhe would prevent <hi>ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and overdoe expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times forced to uſe the <hi>bridle</hi> to her, when the <hi>ſpur</hi> could
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104249:36"/>not ſpring ſome cold mettle profeſſors of far greater abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; the truth is, her <hi>eſtate</hi> was not ſo large as her <hi>heart;</hi> upon which account I have ſometimes left her out of my addreſſes in many works of that nature; for which, when ſhe hath occaſionally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it, ſhe hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, as if a great diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice had been done her.</p>
               <p>The truth is, ſhe had the moſt <hi>generous ſpirit,</hi> and the moſt <hi>liberal hand</hi> that ever I met with in her rank and quality.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A fifth part of her eſtate went in Charity</note> 
                  <hi>By</hi> what I have obſerved, I cannot believe ſhe could give away leſſe in a year then the <hi>fifth part</hi> of her annual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue; And all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>a trumpet,</hi> nay her <hi>left hand KNEW NOT what
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:104249:37"/>her right hand did.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                     <hi>Quest.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> It may be ſome will ask, I but what good hath ſhe done at her death?</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw.</note> 
                  <hi>Somewhat</hi> ſhe hath done; though not much; of which I can give you this twofold accompt. 1. That <hi>Joynctures</hi> are as <hi>mortal</hi> as the perſons themſelves that have them: indeed they dye together. 2. And above all; ſhe did <hi>in her life,</hi> what others doe <hi>at their death,</hi> when they can keep it no longer; ſhe made her own <hi>eyes</hi> her <hi>overſeers,</hi> and her <hi>hands</hi> her <hi>Executors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> her mercy to <hi>ſouls</hi> was not leſſe then her mercy to the <hi>body.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mercy to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That</hi> was one iſſue of her <hi>worldly eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lectures.</note>
                  <hi>Contribution towards the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:104249:37"/>maintaining of Lectures,</hi> in ſuch places where there was ſome <hi>defect</hi> in the <hi>publique meanes</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> her own pariſh in the Country, ſhe encouraged a weekly Lecture (during the time of her retirement in the Country) upon her owne charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Her Houſe</hi> was the <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouze</hi> for the godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery within many miles of her habitation, and her <hi>Table</hi> their <hi>Ordinary,</hi> not only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Lecture dayes,</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>all occaſions.</hi> Thither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired tempted ſouls, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſciences, oppoſed Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, oppreſſed Chriſtians; ſhe was either their <hi>Oracle</hi> or their <hi>Advocate.</hi> Divers <hi>Exiles</hi> of <hi>Hungaria, Tranſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vania, Polonia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exiles.</note> have been
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104249:38"/>nouriſhed and preſerved by her bounty.</p>
               <p>Oh how active to bring it ſoules to Jeſus Chriſt! what pains ſhe took to <hi>inform</hi> the <hi>ignorant,</hi> to <hi>reform</hi> the places where ſhe lived? how ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to promote the power of godlineſs? to gain in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers? to bring out of the ſnare of the Divel <hi>ſuch as were taken captive at his pleaſure?</hi> yet ſtil within her own <hi>line and circle,</hi> ſhe was very <hi>active,</hi> but <hi>no buſibody,</hi> ever <hi>ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> but never <hi>excentrick;</hi> Such a rare skill ſhe had to diſtinguiſh between <hi>doing good,</hi> and medling <hi>out of her ſphere.</hi> And I am humbly confident, as it was her am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, ſo it is her happineſs that <hi>ſhe is not gone to Heaven alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104249:38"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conſtant &amp; conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on publick ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> Sixthly, ſhe was a <hi>conſtant and conſciencious attendant on the publick Ordinanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: Word, Sacrament, Prayer, &amp;c.</hi> She <hi>forſook not the Aſſemblies of the Saints, as the manner of ſome is;</hi> But <hi>watched daily at the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes, and waited at the poſts of wiſdom.</hi> And that with this addition of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.34.</note> 
                  <hi>in her own place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was not a gadding fancifull Profeſſor, who took a pride to be ſeen in <hi>Forreign Aſſemblies;</hi> either to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie an <hi>humour</hi> or to get <hi>a name;</hi> ſhe lookt upon it as a duty to own and ſtrengthen the hands of the Miniſtery under which God had placed her.<note place="margin">She atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in her own place.</note>
               </p>
               <p>She was afraid ſhe ſhould ſin, to <hi>deſert</hi> thoſe, who for their <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> met with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104249:39"/>
                  <hi>oppoſition</hi> enough, beſides, from them that are without.</p>
               <p>She counted it no <hi>Popery</hi> to ſay <hi>my Miniſter, my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> though in the meane time, ſhe was not ignorant of her priviledge,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.22.</note> how that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas</hi> was hers; which priviledge accordingly, ſhe made uſe of, in the proper ſeaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when <hi>Congregational vacancy</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her going abroad.</p>
               <p>Hence, dayes of <hi>publick humiliation, weekly Lectures,</hi> and other occaſional Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies both <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> were the conſtant wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of her unwearied de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: yet all this without the leaſt treſpaſs upon her Domeſtick Affairs: as I ſhall tell you hereafter.</p>
               <p>As thus ſhe was <hi>Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt;</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104249:39"/>So likewiſe was ſhe <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> in her publick atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances.</p>
               <p>The time ſhe ſpent in <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration BEFORE,</hi> and in <hi>reflection</hi> and <hi>meditation AFTER</hi> the ſolemn Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, was incredible; eſpecially conſidering what time ſhe ſpent with her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</p>
               <p>Oh how abundant ſhe was in the work of the Lord, how ſevere in obſerving her times for duty, both Domeſtique and perſonal, and how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to prevent, or evade diſtractions. Surely ſhe was truly what the Father ſaid of St. <hi>Paul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Inſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Dei cultrix.</note> 
                  <hi>An inſatiable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence ſhe attained to a high degree and <hi>eminency</hi> in <hi>holineſs</hi> (you ſee I am faine
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:104249:40"/>to twiſt in the <hi>ſecond ſtrein of excellency</hi> with the firſt.)</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian ſhe was of a moſt <hi>gracious ſpirit,</hi> and a moſt <hi>holy life,</hi> with how much <hi>heavenly mindedneſs</hi> did ſhe winde through a world of unavoidable diſtractions in the world?</p>
               <p>Surely ſhe did weare her Profeſſion with as few ſtains, and carried as unblemiſhed an holineſs with her to Heaven; as moſt Chriſtians whom this generation hath known.</p>
               <p>A woman of a moſt <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> and <hi>profitable Society; The Law of God was in her heart,</hi> Pſal. 37.31. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her <hi>mouth ſpake wiſdom, and her tongue talked of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, verſ.</hi> 30. out of the abundance of <hi>her heart, her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104249:40"/>mouth ſpake to edification,</hi> Matth. 12.34. there is none that ever did converſe with her, but if they did not goe away <hi>better</hi> then they came, it was their own fault.</p>
               <p>She was alwaies <hi>giving</hi> or <hi>taking.</hi> With <hi>weake</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhe would <hi>teach,</hi> with <hi>ſtrong</hi> ſhe would <hi>learn:</hi> with all ſhe would be <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>ſavory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She had <hi>Exquiſitely</hi> got the art of <hi>Time-redemption:</hi> As in the Character here: <hi>ſhe opened her mouth in wiſdome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 31.26.</note> 
                  <hi>and in her t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngue was the law of kindneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stability in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Seventhly, Hence alſo her <hi>ſtability</hi> in judgement.</p>
               <p>Unſetled hearing uſually begets <hi>unſetledneſs in opinion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Erratick hearers (though of the better complexion)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104249:41"/>uſually are not the <hi>moſt ſtable</hi> Chriſtians; they have (many times) their <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncies</hi> and their <hi>why bibbles,</hi> and their crotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets wherewith they doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>trouble</hi> themſelves and others, then <hi>edifie.</hi> She was none of them (through grace;) ſhe ſtood <hi>like a rock</hi> againſt all blaſts of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſme;</hi> and did not only ſtand by her principles, but as a <hi>Daughter of wiſdom,</hi> was in a very good meaſure able to <hi>juſtifie wiſdom,</hi> and give <hi>a reaſon of the hope which was in her.</hi> She was a <hi>well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottomed</hi> Chriſtian; of a ſound judgement:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. ult.</note> ſhe had the <hi>minde of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ninth place, <note place="margin">Ninth.</note> ſhe was not a <hi>cenſorious Chriſtian,</hi> as ſome Profeſſors are who are alwayes <hi>finding fault;</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:104249:41"/>and many times where they cannnot <hi>finde,</hi> the <hi>make</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; and ſeldom have a good word for any but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>But this worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman had much of the character of <hi>charity</hi> in her, <hi>bearing all things believing all things hoping all things and enduring all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.7.</note> wich were any way capable of a fairer interpretation.</p>
               <p>The truth is, ſhe found ſo much work to doe <hi>at home</hi> in her own heart, that ſhe had little leaſure to <hi>ſtir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a pretty Criticiſm that the ſame word in the Greek which ſignifieth <hi>to be idle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or ior, arguo.</note> ſignifieth alſo <hi>to cenſure:</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that <hi>idle Chriſtians are moſt cenſorious.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:104249:42"/>
               <p>She would often ſay to me, that ſhe durſt not too critically enquire into or judge others who came to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> (unleſs ſhe knew them ſcandalous) ſhe had enough to doe, to make out her own right to that tremendous Ordinance.</p>
               <p>Ninethly, ſhe was of <hi>a moſt ſweet and chearfull ſpirit;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> ſhe did not want her <hi>croſſes</hi> and <hi>trials</hi> (and great ones too) yet ſeldom was there a cloud ſeen upon her countenance; the ground Whereof was the <hi>inward ſerenitie</hi> which ſhe poſſeſt in her own ſpirit, in the ſence of Gods love and her intereſt in Chriſt; of which ſhe had moſt <hi>precious Scripture evidence,</hi> which was ballaſt to her ſoule in all weathers. Surely the <hi>joy of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104249:42"/>the Lord was her ſtrength,</hi> Nehem. 18.10.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, and laſtly, She was beyond all parallel; <hi>good in her Relations.</hi> Never <hi>Mother</hi> had a better <hi>C ie:</hi> never <hi>children</hi> bad a better <hi>Mother:</hi> never <hi>Servants</hi> had a better <hi>Governour:</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Friends</hi> a better <hi>Friend:</hi> ſhe fild all her Relations with wiſdom and fidelitie.<note place="margin">verſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my text.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Her Children riſe up and call her bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She was a Mother of ten thouſand to them, Both in reſpect of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">A good mother in temporals.</note> Their <hi>Temporal Eſtates.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Their <hi>Spiritual Eſtates.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As to their Temporals; God wrought little leſs then miraculouſly by her, for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104249:43"/>their aboundant enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Three Sons ſhe had by two ſeveral <hi>Husbands,</hi> to whom ſhe hath left faire and liberal Eſtates, as if they had been all <hi>Elder Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers,</hi> though it was not in the power of their dying Fathers hands to do it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hir Firſt-born, Sir <hi>Howland Roberts</hi> of <hi>Glaſſenbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </note> Her <hi>Firſt-born,</hi> the <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> of his Fathers Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, by her wiſdome and indefatigable induſtry, ſhe hath quietly inveſted into the <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Honorable</hi> Inheritance of his Noble <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors</hi> of <hi>Glaſſenbury</hi> in <hi>Kent:</hi> in the Poſſeſſion of that Ancient Name of the <hi>Roberts,</hi> alias <hi>Rookherſts</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> So make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood <hi>Solomons</hi> character, <hi>the wiſe woman buildeth her houſe,</hi> Pro. 14.1.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:104249:43"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her youngeſt Son.</note> Her <hi>youngeſt Son,</hi> born but to a <hi>third part</hi> of his Ances<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors inheritance; and that alſo not without <hi>incumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> by her incredible pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſhe hath leſt now <hi>Heire Apprent</hi> to the <hi>whole eſtate;</hi> not of a mean conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.<note place="margin">Conghurſt <hi>in</hi> Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt <hi>in</hi> Kent.</note> With the Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar in this <hi>deſcription</hi> of an Execellent woeman, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>She conſidered the field and bought it, and with the fruit of her hands, ſhe planted the vinyard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her <hi>Middle Son; Second</hi> by her firſt huſband,<note place="margin">Her middle ſon.</note> born to little or nothing of his progenitors; by the favour God gave his gracious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſight of her own Honorable family, was adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a very worthy porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Noble inheritance of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104249:44"/>the <hi>Howlands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The elder gracious, the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hopefull</note> For her <hi>two daughters</hi> who were very pretious in her eyes, She hath Secured <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> not beneath their living Fathers honour though far above their dying abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>It is wonderfull in my eyes that ſhe ſhould provide ſo fully for all her children out of ſuch a narrow and perplexed eſtate as fell to her managing by her Huſbands, for certainely the world (as it is uſually) did <hi>overvalue</hi> her <hi>incoms</hi> and <hi>undervalue</hi> her <hi>iſſues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay it is not leſs then a miracle to any that ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider it that ſhe ſhould <hi>have</hi> ſo <hi>little,</hi> (comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) and <hi>doe</hi> ſo <hi>much;</hi> both for her <hi>one family</hi> and for the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104249:44"/>
                  <hi>Houſhold of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She gave to <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> as if ſhe had forgotten her own <hi>Children;</hi> and ſo provided for her <hi>Children</hi> as if ſhe had been a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to works of <hi>mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But doubtleſs <hi>God was with her</hi> and made good the Miſtery of the widows <hi>Cruſe of Oyle,</hi> &amp; handful of <hi>Meale,</hi> for the <hi>paying of her debts,</hi> &amp; <hi>preſerving</hi> of her Family.</p>
               <p>This worthy Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was not leſs a Mother to them in <hi>Spirituals</hi> then in <hi>temporals:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A good mother in ſpirituals.</note> the neglect whereof is the great <hi>ſinne</hi> of moſt <hi>Parents,</hi> and the <hi>ruine</hi> of their Children;<note place="margin">I b. 39.13.14.15.16.</note> of whom we may ſay as <hi>Job</hi> of the <hi>Ostrich, She leaveth her Eggs in the Earth, and warmeth them in the duſt; and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104249:45"/>forgetteth that the foor may cruſh them, or that the wild beaſts may breake them; ſhe is hardened againſt her young ones, as though they were not hers: her labour is in vaine without feare, becauſe God hath deprived her of wiſdom, neither hath he imparted unto her underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moſt of Parents, if they can but <hi>Earth</hi> their Children enough, and <hi>warn</hi> them in the <hi>Duſt,</hi> the <hi>Duſt-heapes</hi> of the world, if they can but <hi>lade them with thick Clay,</hi> as <hi>Habbakkuk</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſilver and gold:<note place="margin">Hab. 2.6.</note> they think they have provided well for them: in the mean time th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y conſider not that the <hi>foot</hi> of <hi>temptation</hi> may cruſh them, or that <hi>wilde bruitiſh luſts</hi> may deſtroy
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104249:45"/>them, they remember not that in all this proviſion heaped up, there is nothing done for the <hi>immortal ſoule;</hi> nothing laid in that may be a <hi>fence</hi> againſt <hi>temptation,</hi> or a preſervative againſt <hi>ſin:</hi> ſo much their <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened</hi> againſt their young ones; as though either they <hi>were not theirs,</hi> or, <hi>as if they had no ſouls. Their labour is in vain;</hi> all the care and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel for their Children is <hi>fruitleſs,</hi> laid out only upon <hi>emptie vanities,</hi> which <hi>periſh in the uſing,</hi> and their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with them,</hi> forever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intervening grace.</p>
               <p>The Reaſon followeth; The <hi>god of this world</hi> hath deprived them of ſaving wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and hath ſhut their eyes againſt ſpiritual under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:104249:46"/>
               <p>This precious <hi>Handman</hi> of the Lord was not ſo: Her great care was to make them <hi>good,</hi> rather then <hi>great;</hi> rich in <hi>grace,</hi> rather then rich in the <hi>world.</hi> Her word was towards them that of the Apoſtle, <hi>my little children of whom I travel in birth again,</hi> (or the ſecond time) till <hi>Chriſt be formed in you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal 3.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I am confident their <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual birth</hi> coſt her more throws and ſorrows; more cries and tears then ever their <hi>natural</hi> did. Her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were all (to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to her, what <hi>Aug.</hi> was to <hi>Monica, Children of many tears and prayers,</hi> which are all upon the <hi>file in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> and I am humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, <hi>anſwers of peace</hi> are preparing for them; they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104249:46"/>were all <hi>the Children of her vows.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the care and pains ſhe took for their holy <hi>educa i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</hi> what perpetual labour did that gracious foule take in <hi>Catechiſing</hi> them in the princples of Religion,<note place="margin">Chatechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually dropping in holy inſtructions!</p>
               <p>How carefull was ſhe that they ſhould <hi>ſanctifie the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath?</hi> read the Scriptures? repeat Sermons? wherein all of them had attained to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent abilities, ſome by <hi>pen,</hi> the reſt (even the * youngeſt by <hi>memory:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not above nine or ten yeares of age.</note>) her Methods and Travell herein were incredible.</p>
               <p>Surely, in all theſe reſpects, as it is here ſaid of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent woman,<note place="margin">verſe 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Her Children riſe up and call her bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:104249:47"/>
               <p>They doe, and they <hi>have cauſe</hi> ſo to doe; and great need they have to look that the <hi>Harveſt</hi> be anſwerable to the <hi>ſeed;</hi> leſt otherwiſe, their Education riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them in time to come; and they have cauſe to <hi>curſe themſelves</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>bleſſing her;</hi> and to wiſh they had been born of a <hi>Turk</hi> or an <hi>Infidel,</hi> rather then of ſo holy a Mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I hope better things, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her care of her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</note> 
                  <hi>Her ſervants</hi> have not leſt cauſe to bleſs her, then her Children; whoſe <hi>Spiritual ſoule good</hi> ſhe tendered as if they had all been the fruit of her owne bowels: They ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with her Children in her pious <hi>diſcipline</hi> and <hi>inſtruction</hi> according to their ſeveral ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:104249:47"/>ſhe would caution them to prepare for holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,<note place="margin">Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</note> and enquire how it was with them after the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was finiſhed, what they remembred? what impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions they found upon their Spirits? She would be often conferring wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h them about their <hi>Evidences,</hi> always cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon them to <hi>get a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom,</hi> to <hi>work out their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with fear and trembling, and to redeem the time.</p>
               <p>I had almoſt ſaid ſhe had none in her Family but <hi>godly ſervants;</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe if ſhe did not <hi>finde</hi> them <hi>ſuch,</hi> ſhe would labour to <hi>make</hi> them <hi>ſuch,</hi> at leaſt conformable to the outward duties of religion; which if any after due admonition re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, ſhe would not retain
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104249:48"/>them longer in her Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">She had a ſpirit of prayer.</note> She practiſed much <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Platform of <hi>Occon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government</hi> in the to Pſalm.</p>
               <p>She had an excellent <hi>Spirit of Prayer,</hi> but accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a rare <hi>modeſty,</hi> for though (when ſhe had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chaplain in her houſe,) ſhe was able to perform the duty in her own perſon with much judgement &amp; affection, Yet in the preſence of thoſe for whom ſhe conceived that work more proper, ſhe could not be tempted to undertak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it, with the greateſt Solicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and importunity.</p>
               <p>In a word to cloſe this firſt branch of Excellency, ſhe was a ſincere practiſer of that Evangelical Rule.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104249:48"/>
                  <hi>Whatſoever things are true,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> 
                  <hi>whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report,</hi> if there were <hi>any ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;</hi> and if there were any <hi>praiſe,</hi> theſe were the things ſhe <hi>thought of,</hi> theſe were the things ſhe purſued with life and vigour.</p>
               <p>And thus I have done with the firſt <hi>Ingredient</hi> Her Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in grace.</note> The <hi>ſecond</hi> is her <hi>Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;</hi> as ſhe was <hi>univerſal,</hi> ſo ſhe was <hi>eminent</hi> in goodneſs.</p>
               <p>But herein I have prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf in the <hi>univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> neither could I avoid it; I could not ſpeak of her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, but I muſt mention alſo her <hi>Eminency</hi> in thoſe graces.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:104249:49"/>
               <p>And it is well; for if that were yet to doe, I might be over burthen ſome.</p>
               <p>I ſhall adde only the word; that this Noble Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; <hi>ſhe was as much above the ſize of other Profeſſors as they are above the ſize of other men and women,</hi> not only <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally</hi> good, but moſt <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thirdly, and laſtly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe was eminently good, ſo ſhe was <hi>perſeveringly</hi> good.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance.</note> She was <hi>no wavering Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:</hi> And the reaſon is, becauſe ſhe built not upon the <hi>ſand</hi> but upon the <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> not upon the ſand of <hi>imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (the Rule that moſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> up their Religion by) but upon the <hi>Rock</hi> and <hi>Found<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Scripture evidence: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a moſt <hi>Noble B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rean;</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:104249:49"/>She took up nothing upon truſt <hi>but ſearched the Scriptures whither thoſe things were ſo</hi> which were delivered unto her in the Miniſtry of the Goſpell.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. of an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, ſhe <hi>began betimes and endured to the end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It pleaſed God to convert her preſently after her firſt <hi>marriage,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">about 26 yeares ſince.</note> when (as ſhe hath often acknowledged) ſhe before was <hi>a vaine Creature</hi> carried away into the ſame <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>faſhions,</hi> and <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of God</hi> and of religion as other of her rank were. The occaſion of her converſion was by a dangerous fall from an horſe,<note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of her Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for in the dayes of her vanity ſhe delighted much to ride a hunting; in her vehement purſuit of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104249:50"/>which games Jeſus Chriſt met her as once he did Paul and <hi>unhorſt</hi> her, ſo that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at his feet and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in her ſelf the <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of death</hi> both <hi>temporal</hi> &amp; <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> ſhe began to cry out (as he did) with trembling and aſtoniſhment, <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do, Act.</hi> 9.6.</p>
               <p>Soon after her converſion while it was but yet <hi>twylight</hi> with her ſhe unhappily fel in to the hands of ſome <hi>Sectaries</hi> who did rather <hi>perplex</hi> her then <hi>pervert</hi> her;<note place="margin">How ſhe fell into the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> but God was graciouſly pleaſed to make a ſpeedy reſcue of this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der convert, by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and wiſdome of a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend holy Miniſter of an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Congregation,<note place="margin">But was ſeaſonably reſcued.</note> with the care and watchfulneſſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104249:50"/>of divers other judicious Chriſtians who were jealous over her with an holy jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy.</p>
               <p>I ſaid [unhappily] but I muſt recal that word (though no thanks to the ſeducer) Godmade it an <hi>happy occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of much good to her ſoul, for the ſnare being once bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; ſhe eſcaped like a bird out of it, ſhe <hi>hated heriſies &amp; ſchiſm with a greater hatred;</hi> and ſtood unſhaken in the truth of God, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Saints to her dying day. From that time ſhe girded up her loines &amp; rejoyced like a mighty man refreſheth with wine to run her race.</p>
               <p>From that time I ſay God carryed on the <hi>work of grace</hi> gloriouſly in her ſoul. <hi>Her
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104249:51"/>goodneſſe was no morning cloud, not early dew that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away.</hi> But as the <hi>morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing light which ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 4.18.</note> the Heb. is to be tranſlated word for word thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The way of the juſt is as a light ſhining and growing and enlightning unto, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the prepared day.</hi> The deſcription agreeth ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this Saint of God; the grace of God in her, was a <hi>light</hi> very conſpicuous, <hi>ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in a <hi>Goſpel adorning</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and <hi>growing</hi> or <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> ſtill <hi>aſcending</hi> and <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſtrength</hi> and <hi>illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating;</hi> Scattering beames of <hi>of light</hi> and <hi>warmth</hi> untill the <hi>prepared day,</hi> or <hi>perfect day,</hi> the day that is <hi>prepared unto perfection,</hi> And
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104249:51"/>oh how earely did this ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſtian attaine to her prepared perfection! <hi>Her Sun did ſet at none day.</hi> She was tranſlated into the other <hi>Orb of glory,</hi> when ſhe had finiſhed little more then halfe her courſe in the <hi>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament</hi> of grace, and the reaſon was becauſe <hi>ſhee did much work in a little time;</hi> ſhe <hi>ran a pace,</hi> and therefore ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived the earlier at her <hi>jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When ſhe came to dye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Her death.</note> ſhe had nothing to doe but to dye, <hi>her work was done;</hi> ſhe had <hi>oyl</hi> in her <hi>veſſel</hi> as well as <hi>oyl</hi> in her <hi>lamp,</hi> her <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> were in a <hi>readineſſe;</hi> her <hi>evidences</hi> were <hi>clared,</hi> her <hi>intereſt</hi> in Chriſt was <hi>ſealed</hi> upon her heart by the <hi>ſpirit of promiſe;</hi> And She her ſelf
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104249:52"/>ſtood alwayes as it were at the doore of her Tabernacle <hi>waiting for her Lord: when he ſhould return from the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> that when he came and knockt,<note place="margin">Lu. 12.35.</note> She might o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to him immediately.</p>
               <p>And happy it was for her ſhe was ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared; <hi>for death gave her but little warning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Her death</note> not that it killed her outright at the firſt ſtroke; but in as much as the nature of her diſtemper was ſuch, as that ſeazing firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her <hi>ſpirits,</hi> it rendred her uncapable of <hi>ſpeaking much,</hi> or having much <hi>ſpoken to her;</hi> the preventing whereof was the ſpeciall care and charge of her Doctors.</p>
               <p>So that had ſhe had her evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences to ſeek when ſhe ſhould have had them to uſe,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104249:52"/>her graces to get when ſhe ſtood in need of her graces; death might have bin indeed a <hi>ſurpriſe</hi> to her of the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt conſequence imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Hence I ſay from the firſt of her ſickneſſe to the laſt,<note place="margin">She ſpake not but very ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</note> ſhe ſpake not <hi>much,</hi> but what ſhe did ſpeake was <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>heavenly;</hi> upon the firſt ſeizure of her diſtemper, ſhe called her two daughters to her and renewed Joſhuahs charge upon them to <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>ſerve the Lord,</hi> and to <hi>feare him;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Fever in her Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its.</note> 
                     <hi>to take heed of ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; as they deſired God ſhould take care of them.</hi>
                  </q> From the time ſhe kept her bed ſhe would be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpeaking with holy admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>how infinitely good God</hi>
                     <hi>had bin unto her evere ſince
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:104249:53"/>he had bin pleaſed to reveal his Son in her.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal</hi> 1.16.</note> She did often expreſs St Paul his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>indifference to life or death,</hi>
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>I am willing to die, and yet contented to live if I may doe more ſervice for God.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.22.22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>My ſelfe ſtanding by her once, I ſaid to her, you would be glad to be gone from us, would ye not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe turned her head, and with a ſweet ſmile replyed, <q rend="inline">I <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to leave you, but I would be glad to be with Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If ſhe were aſkt, how ſhe did, ſhe would ſometimes anſwer, <q rend="inline">I <hi>am the Lords Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,</hi>ſometimes, <hi>An admirour of free graces and ſo I deſire to be.</hi>
                  </q> She
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104249:53"/>was very willing to take whatſoever was adviſed; and would often <hi>heavenlize</hi> earth-refreſhings with ſpirituall contemplation, <hi>Oh this is very good and pleaſant would ſhe ſay; and if this be ſo good oh how ſweet is my good God? how pleaſant is Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Her expreſſions were but <hi>ſhort,</hi> but very <hi>ſweet;</hi> an heavenly <hi>ejaculation</hi> or two and then <hi>ſilence</hi> for a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time. Her daughters ſtanding by her beds ſide, ſhe beſpake them after this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Oh children how ſweet and precious is Christ, but oh how bitter a thing is ſin?</hi> and after a little breathing: <hi>Be ſure to get an intereſt in Christ and try your faith.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>To the Nurſes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:104249:54"/>that came to turn her in her bed (for the Fever that had accended her ſpirits) and exhauſted her ſtrength ſo faſt in a few dayes, that ſhe was not able to turn, or help her ſelfe in the leaſt meaſure, ſhe would ſay, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>I am very weak; but my God is very ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rong, and there is my comfort, he will lift me up.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Her elder daughter out of a childe-like deſire of her life: would. Sometime ſay.</p>
               <p>Mother I hope the <hi>Lord</hi> in much mercy will reſtore you to us againe;</p>
               <p>To which ſhe retuned <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>what God pleaſeth; if ho have no more work for me to doe then I am exceeding willing to dye and to be with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:104249:54"/>Chriſt which is beſt of all, but if God doe recover me, the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> give me more grace that I may walk anſwerably to his mercies.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the Sabbath morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it being <hi>Sacrament day,</hi> her eldeſt daughter came to take her leave of her ſaying.</p>
               <p>Mother, I am going to Church and to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is well, ſaid ſhe, but</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>I cannot go, only be ſure to go in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rength of Chriſt, and doe all your duties in his ſtrength, knowing that we have none of our own to doe any thing that is good, &amp; the Lord goe with you;</hi>
                  </q> with many other gracious words which dropt like hony from her lips.</p>
               <p>The younger daughter
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:104249:55"/>ſtaying at home, ſhe askt her (according to her conſtant uſe) childe what do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member of what you have read? and when the childe repeated ſome portion of it, ſhe anſwered,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>It is well, but be ſure to practiſe it.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And then ſhe would break out again, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Oh how ſweet is Jeſus Chriſt, but what an ougly thing is ſin.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>When the evening came, ſhe called to her elder daughter, to go and repeate the Sermons ſhe had heard in the Family, as ſhe uſed to doe.</p>
               <p>On the next day coming to viſit her, I found her very weake, yet I preſumed on ſo much liberty as to hint a word or two, to this purpoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:104249:55"/>I hope ye have found no want of a Sabbath the laſt day; though God tye us to means, he doth not tye him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to means, the <hi>preſence of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> I hope hath abundantly compenſated the <hi>abſence of the Ordinances!</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Yea,</hi> (ſhe replyed) <hi>I I ſate under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet unto my taſte.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>She was from thence (for ſome houres) under a kinde of <hi>delirium;</hi> but it was very calm and gracious, for that night the Curtains being drawn (and all attendants enjoyned ſilence by the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians) ſhe lay praying the greateſt part of the night, with as much ſweetneſs and ſavor as in her health: And when the Maids and Nurſes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:104249:56"/>came about her, ſhe wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeak moſt ſenſibly to them <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Oh labour to make your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and election ſure, get an intereſt in Chriſt while you are in health and ſtrength.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>After this the diſtemper working more in her head, occaſioned her to ſpeake ſomewhat <hi>erratickly,</hi> though (bleſſed bee God) never <hi>uncomely;</hi> Yea and if any good notion were hinted, ſhe would cloſe with it very ſweetly, and chiding her ſelf would ſay in a very ſenſible manner, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>My fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh fancy runs upon abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of other things, that I cannot stay my thoughts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God as I would.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo continued ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:104249:56"/>much to her ſelf and her God, though not very <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly,</hi> yet all very <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the time ſhe kept her Chamber, which was from Wedneſday till Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, ſhe never ſpake of any <hi>wordly affairs;</hi> and if her ſervant had come to ask her any queſtion in order to her temporal affairs, ſhe would ſay to him, oh do not trouble me with any of theſe things on the <hi>Sabbath day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">During the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of her ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>For that was one of her happy miſtakes, <hi>ſhe thought all the whole time was Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And truly ſo it was to her: <hi>The Law of the Sabbath was was eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aven upon her heart;</hi> what others wickedly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:104249:57"/>(indeed to the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Sabbath,</hi> not to the <hi>ſpirituallizing of then converſations</hi>) was real in this holy ſervant of Chriſt. <hi>Every day was a Sabbath with her,</hi> eſpecially upon her death-bed, as ſhe drew nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and nearer to that <hi>reſt which remaines for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God;</hi> ſhe was wrought into a more ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble frame of heart to <hi>that everlaſting Sabbath</hi> her moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heaven-ward was <hi>natural, motions are ſtronger &amp; ſwifter towards the center, after which</hi> ſhe <hi>aſpired,</hi> and <hi>into which</hi> ſhe <hi>expired:</hi> And in which ſhe now triumpheth with <hi>Him whom her ſoule loved,</hi> and with the <hi>Spirits of juſt men made perfect;</hi> and all
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:104249:57"/>the Elect Angels of God to all Eternity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thanks be to God for his unſpeakable gift.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:58"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104249:58"/>
            <head>Several Letters from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Miniſters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Life and Death of Miſtreſſe <hi>ELIZABETH SCOTT,</hi> with a Narrative un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her own hand of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable experiences, and the gracious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God towards her.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Mr. <hi>Naltons</hi> Letter to Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong many ſad ſignes, and ſymptoms of Gods diſpleaſure towards the land, I look on this, as not the leaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Gods remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many of his precious Saints
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104249:59"/>and ſervants from among us, who while they were in the land of the Living) helped to keep off the ſtorm of Gods anger, and to turn away his indignation from a God-provoking people. Oh that our hearts were more deeply affected with it! that we might feelingly ſay with the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (<hi>chap.</hi> 16. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>My bowels ſhall ſound like a harp for</hi> England; Yea, <hi>we will ſigh with the breaking of our loines,</hi> Ezek. 21.6. One choice Jewel among the reſt, God has of late gathered to his Cabinet, namely, pious, precious, Miſtreſſe <hi>Scott;</hi> Concerning whom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you deſired my concurrent Teſtimony, as being one ſo well known to me, having been a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my Congregation for divers years together, till ſhe came to be under your charge: I have this to ſay; She was a Gentlewoman of a choice ſpirit, of a marvelous
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104249:59"/>ſweet temper and diſpoſition, of an amiable winning carriage, and of a truly pious and Religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. She was one that made Religion her buſineſſe, her <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not her <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: She made it her conſtant courſe vigorouſly to drive a Trade for heaven, and to be preſſing towards the mark, <hi>even the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> She was not like thoſe, that <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>qui utuntur Deo, ut fruantur mundo;</hi> But ſhe made uſe of the world, but as a foot-ſtool, to raiſe up her ſoul to the enjoyment of God, as her portion for ever. She was not weary of Gods ſervice, like thoſe hypocrites that ſaid, <hi>what a weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is it,</hi> Mal. 1.13. but duty was her delight, and ſin her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt burden: The world did not make her weary of duty, but duty made her weary of the world; Her conſtant frequenting of Ordi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104249:60"/>(wherein ſhe was both emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and exemplary) her cloſeſt retirements, wherein ſhe ſaw of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a glimpſe of that glory which ſhe now enjoys in the boſom of Jeſus Chriſt, made her long earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be at her fathers houſe, and to breath out her <hi>Cupio deſolvi,</hi> Oh that I might be with him whom my ſoul loveth! In brief, ſhe made haſte to heaven, lived much in a little time; holding forth the Word of life, by a holy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted profeſſion, holding faſt the Word of Truth by a conſtant and undaunted Reſolution, and ſo finiſhed her courſe with joy. Therefore I conceive, that this Text which you ſweetly opened at her Funeral, was rightly and ſuitably applied to her, <hi>Many daughters have done virtuouſly,</hi> &amp;c. This Teſtimony I have given not for her ſake, that is dead, but for the ſake of thoſe that are living.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104249:60"/>
                  <hi>The dead praiſe not the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 115.17. Look as the dead return no praiſes to the living God, ſo neither do they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard any praiſes from living men; Our commendations cannot help them, our diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations cannot hurt them, as our prayers cannot reach them, ſo neither can our praiſes profit them; But happy ſurely are they, that can tread in the Steps of thoſe bleſſed Saints, that have gone before us; <hi>whoſe faith follow,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>conſidering the end of their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Heb. 13.7. If we do as they did, we ſhall ſpeed as they ſped; The Lord of his infinite mercy, help us to ſerve our generation faithfully (as this eminent godly Gentlewoman did) that we may do every days duty with Chriſtian chearfulneſſe, and bear every days burden with Chriſtian patience, and in the midſt of all changes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104249:61"/>ſtraites and ſtormes, hold out with Chriſtian perſeverance, that <hi>in the end of our dayes, we may receive the end of our hopes, even the ſalvation of our ſouls;</hi> It is and ſhall be the hearty prayer of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your affectionate loving Friend and Brother in the Lords Work. <hi>JA. NALTON.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104249:61"/>
               <head>Mrs. <hi>SCOTS</hi> own writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which ſhe hath left under her own hand.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Little before her death, ſhe began to write in a book her experiences of Gods goodneſs to her, and intended to have filled it up, but ſhe was taken away before ſhe had done many leaves of it; onely ſhe had written before, divers things in ſome papers.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In the Book ſhe beginneth and proceedeth thus.</head>
                  <p>SOme notes to keep ſpeciall things in my remembrance, that I may be quickned to anſwer
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104249:62"/>Gods ends, in all his gracious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to me, to whom all his ways have been mercy and truth; and I deſire, my ways towards him, may be conſtrained obedience, from faith and love, wrought by his ſpirit in my heart, in all things.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How God did effectually call me at firſt to himſelf.</head>
                  <p>I was born a child of wrath, and an heir of hell, and in my youth, was very vile and vain; Yet I did duties in a formal way, and was very confident God did love me, and of my good eſtate: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſixteen and ſeventeen I was married, and about nineteen year old as I was riding, it being hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, I fell down and put my leg out of joynt, which was a great miſery to me, but in that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, God did work on me with ſome convictions and reſolutions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104249:62"/>if I were well again to walk in Gods wayes; afterward inquiring, his Providence brought Mr. <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields</hi> Book to me, the Marrow of Divinity, and in reading of it, God did convince me of my abundant abominable ſins: I made a cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of them I could remember, and was in much trouble for them under the ſpirit of bondage, I think ſome moneths: but I have forgotten how long; but God made ſinne very bitter to me, and broke my heart for my ſinne, and from my ſinne: and I know God broke my heart, becauſe his love did it, many a tear of Love did I ſhed in the boſom of my God. When the ſpirit of Adoption was come to me, then how did I mourn for ſinning againſt the Lord, and diſhonouring of his dear Name? But when I was in the pangs of the Spirit of bondage and new birth, I had great troubles
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104249:63"/>of Conſcience, and grievous pangs and after that, dreadfull baſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thoughts, and fain would I have run away from God, looked upon his wayes as grievous, and had hard thoughts of him, but yet the Lord would not let me go, but carried me through, that I had no power to leave ſeeking of him, and did unhook me, and brought me to keep Faſts by my ſelf, and to humble my ſoul before him, and ſhewed me how vile I was in a great meaſure, and made me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſinnes with ſhame and ſorrow; Then after this, he made me cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt in a promiſe, and gave me full aſſurance that all my ſins were pardoned by the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt fully, and I gave up my ſelf in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to him, and by his ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and ſhining of his face, and comforts of his ſpirit, and grace, he hath made me hate the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104249:63"/>moſt ſweet and ſecret ſin; and my hatred of all ſin appears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I deſire the death of it, and deſire to be freed from the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſweeteſt pleaſure of the moſt ſecret ſin, that I may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy communion with my God, whoſe love is farre better than life: and I deſire ſo to eſteem it. God hath brought me to Chriſt, and hath made me put on his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and hath given me to Chriſt, and given Chriſt to me, and I know it certainly that God did chooſe me from all eternity, becauſe he hath made me to give up my ſelf to Jeſus Chriſt for theſe ends that Jeſus Chriſt gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for me; That by believing, I might give God the glory of his free grace and faithfullneſſe, and that my ſinnes might be pardoned and mortified, and that I may be ſanctified and made holy by him, redeemed from all iniquity, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104249:64"/>vain converſation, and made a peculiar ſervant of his, zealous of good works, that I may honour him in bearing forth much fruit, and be fully acted by his ſpirit and grace, for the glory of his name in all things, that Jeſus Chriſt may ſee the travail of his ſoul in me, as much as I am capable, ſo long as I have a being, that I may admire free grace. God hath given me Jeſus Chriſt by faith, oftentimes in Sacraments, Word, and Prayer, and Meditation, by the conduit pipes of his Ordinances. And I live by Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe his Spirit liveth in me in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, convincing, guiding, and councelling of me; And my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is, to honour him as much as I am capable for ever, in his life, and ſtrength, and ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Thus farre Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the ſaid Book, when the Lord took her from recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104249:64"/>and improving his gracious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences to her here, to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and perfect enjoyments of himſelf above.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Other Writings that Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi> hath left, concerning Gods goodneſſe to her.</head>
                  <p>ABout the middle of <hi>April,</hi> 1645. there was the ſecond riſing in <hi>Kent,</hi> and I was grievouſly perplexed, thinking my husband, jewels, goods, and all I had, and my life, ſhould have then by the riſers been taken from me, and I was in exceeding fear, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured God by over much weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſorrowing before others, but that night I heard the Riſers were ſuppreſſed, then I had much joy, and reſolved through Gods ſtrength that my heart ſhould be weaned from the world, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I lookt for much help from,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104249:65"/>but I found none; I ſaw it was empty: then reſolved I alſo to leave reſting upon it, and to ſpend my life, and ſtrength, and meanes of grace, to the uttermoſt advantage of Gods glory, and my ſouls eternall good; and never to ſin away any opportunity of doing good, and ſervice for his glory: Thus did I ſee, that this great ſtraight, and dark Providence of the Lord wrought abundantly for my good. Two days after, I did in private by my ſelf keep a day of faſt, and had ſome grief for my own ſin and others, and had ſome comfort in Gods acceptance, though I was much wanting in the performance of the ſame. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my faſt day, there was a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick day of thankſgiving for that mercy of ſubduing the Riſers, my ſpirit was much ſadded, that my heart was no more in frame ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſaid day, that I did no
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104249:65"/>more rejoyce in God in it. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward I had ſweet aſſurance of Gods eternall love, and ſaw much vanity and emptineſſe in all earthly things, and deſired to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my converſation aright. Again I kept another private day of faſt by my ſelf, and though much diſtempered yet had ſome hopes of acceptance. I kept another day of private faſt by my ſelf, to ſeek to God for more grace, to honour him, and that God would do alſo the ſame in my husband that he might honour God.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1647. a little after my husband died, my heart was exceedingly out of frame, but a Sabbath day at night the Lord came ſweetly to me, in perſwading me to truſt in him from what he had done; So I had ſweet aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his Eternal love through Chriſt at prayer, and the pardon of all my ſinnes, and gave my
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104249:66"/>ſelf to him to do with me what he would, and ſo the temptation and thoſe thoughts went away, and I had ſweet peace. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward we kept a faſt in the family, to humble our ſelves for the breach in the death of my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and then I had great deſires to honour God in my place, and gave up my ſelf to God and had peace, and afterward ſweet aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that I was his. This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Hawkherſt</hi> I was not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as I ought to have been, the day before I loſt my frame of grace exceedingly, by my unſenſibleneſs of <hi>Irelands</hi> miſery, and being mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry when I ſhould have ſorrowed, and on the Lords day morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I went to the Sacrament, I had a grievous temptation, as if I might live without ordinances, and as if there were no neceſſity of them; O this deaded my heart to the duty, yet my faith fought
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104249:66"/>with it, and brought me to the Lords ſupper, where I received Chriſt, and gave my ſelf to him, and found ſweet comfort and ſtrength from Chriſt in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and I do reſolve in Chriſts ſtrength, to walk holily and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with God all my dayes to his honour, and to cleave cloſe to Chriſt in all his Ordinances, whilſt I can enjoy them. Being repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by one, my heart did greatly riſe, and I found I was not willing to ſubmit to Gods will and wayes in all things, but I had a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, and was reſolved to ſubmit to God in all, and ſaw more of my heart and the world then ever, and I had ſweet influence from God and ſhinings of his face in prayer. The next Lords day after I had received the Sacrament, I went to the Sacrament again, my Lord having by a providence provided another feaſt for me, knowing my
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104249:67"/>neceſſities; and I did ſit under Chriſts ſhadow, and did receive his body and bloud by faith. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sacrament at evening I had very ſweet fruits and effects of Chriſt in me. Another Sacrament afterward I was much failing and wanting in doing my duty and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my grace, but God gave me Chriſt in free grace, and I deſire to live by faith upon him, to him and his glory, giving my ſelf to the Lord to be his, and not mine own; and deſire to live on Chriſt as my portion and ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>In <hi>January,</hi> 1650. Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi> began another, of the ſweet expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences (writes ſhe) my God hath given me of his faithfull perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of his Word and Promiſe to me. In <hi>January</hi> 1650. The Lord ſweetly told me in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of his Word, out of the fourth <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> the eighth <hi>Verſe,</hi> how <hi>Chriſt had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104249:67"/>led captivity captive</hi> in me, and for me in ſome meaſure; the ſame day, an occaſion there was that cauſed my corruptions much to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, but my God according to his Word did lead that captivity cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and at night God gave me ſweet comings in of himſelf into my ſould, and ſweet aſſurance, and ſome experience of the true &amp; real work of Grace in me, &amp; how God made the riſings of ſinne the ruine of ſin in me by Chriſt. The Lord gave me very ſweet experience of his power in preſerving me, when two in my family had the ſmall pox, and three the meaſels, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his word in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.7. <hi>It ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi> O never diſtruſt thy God more. After this, God did ſhew me in ſome meaſure the curſed vileneſs of my nature, and ſuffered that bitter root of blaſphemy to riſe up in my heart, and God did this to puniſh
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104249:68"/>me, for my vain and ſinfull thoughts, but Jeſus Chriſt made my faith to fight againſt it, but it was very ſad and bitter to me, and after I was buffeted, God made me ſee the vileneſſe of ſinne, and ſinful thoughts, and made me in his ſtrength reſolve againſt all ſin, and to hate it, and to walk colſely with my God, and chuſe rather to offend all the world, then commit the leaſt ſinne, and to loſe all, and ſuffer all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, rather then commit the leaſt ſin; For God can make ones own heart and conſcience a hell to one, and ones bed and all ones com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts bitter as death. And I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to prize mercy, and cloſe walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with God, to lie down and riſe up with him, and to pitty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; This precious experience and leſſon God taught me by that affliction, as by many other, and drave ſin and vain thoughts from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104249:68"/>me in ſome meaſure, making Chriſt ſweet, and fulfilling his Word, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. My God doth give me ſweet experience of the growth of grace in my ſoul, and all from the virtue of Chriſts blood. Before this Sacrament, my preparations were not ſo great as they ſhould have been, but my God did drive me from reſting on any thing in my ſelf, and brought me to him without money and without price, and gave me ſweet aſſurance of the truth of the work of grace on my heart; I love him becauſe he loved me firſt, and with his loving kindneſſe did he draw me. This Sabbath when I went to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſaw my preparation ſmall and my thoughts not ſo ſweet as they ſhould, but my heart deſiring the Lord to order my thoughts aright, and act my graces in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of the 23 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> before
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104249:69"/>morning Sermon, God ſweetly melted me in ſome meaſure with ſome teares of love, and after did as it were ſweetly take me by the hand, ſet me down at his table, and comfortably intimated it was my portion, and ſo I ſat under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet unto my taſte, and God did act my faith to take Chriſt, and pardon, ſanctification, mortification in his bloud, and ſealed deliverance from temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by his body broken and bloud ſhed, and all the fruits thereof; ſome effects I had afterward, and the Word was ſweet, and I came home rejoycing and reſolving to live and die, to and for and with God, giving my ſelf for ever to him, to live and move all in him and by him, to reſt upon his word, and promiſe, and expect to live by him according to it; I deſire to have ſuch a day again to receive
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104249:69"/>Chriſt, I was many wayes failing, all is free grace, God doth all that is good in me, for I am a hell by nature, but I have found moſt precious vertue in the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, that it hath in ſome meaſure meekened my ſpirit and overcome wicked thoughts in me. Next Sacrament I was failing in my preparation and acting of my graces, and was troubled I had no more light of Gods countenance, and my corrupt nature was apt to riſe: but God kept it down, and afterward taught me theſe leſſons by it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That ſin was not ſo bitter to me, nor ſo bitterly bewailed by me, as it ought; the more bitter ſin is, the ſweeter is Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That God would have me prize Ordinances to enjoy Chriſt, but not to reſt upon them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That I ſhould live by faith
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104249:70"/>and not by ſence, yea though there be no ſence.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That Gods loving counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is better then life, and that God would have me depending, and contented with whatſoever he will give: O that I could learn and practiſe theſe leſſons, which were precious fruits of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. This Sacrament I was failing in my meditation, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and excitation, and my dead heart much hindred me in the ſervice of the living God, but the Lord brought me to his table with ſome aſſurance it was my portion, and I ſat under his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and he acted my graces, I deſire to magnifie free grace, and to expect ſtrength from him to do it according to the Covenant ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his bloud. This Sacrament I had ſome ſweet actings of faith above ſence, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that God was my father
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104249:70"/>and his power and wiſdom would order all things for my good. This Sacrament, though I did not mourn for my ſins that did ſlay my Saviour, nor act ſacramentall repentance as I ought, yet by faith I received Jeſus Chriſt, and came home with ſome comfort, and had ſome ſoftneſſe of heart. I had ſweet expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ience of my Gods anſwering my prayer in the very thing I deſired. This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though I did not receive ſo much of Chriſt as I deſired, yet I had ſome ſweet effects of his blood, in reſolving in his ſtrength not to give way to unbelief nor ſin and deſiring to come again to his Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>This day I was at a faſt, and God came ſweetly in and melted my heart, and made his promiſe good, that they that wait on him ſhall renew their ſtrength, God ſweetly anſwered my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:104249:71"/>mercy for one of my children. This day I did receive Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament, and came home rejoycing, and aſſured my ſinnes were pardoned, and that Chriſt could as well be pulled out of heaven, as I pulled from Chriſt. I renewed my Covenant, I gave my ſelf to my God for his ſervice for ever. This Sacrament I did receive Jeſus Chriſt, and ſweet influence from him, and I deſire to honour him in all things for ever, in my ſoul, body, eſtate, will, affections and all; I, and all I have are his, and to be at his ruling in all things at all times; Theſe are fruits of Chriſts bloud, I deſire to bear about the world with me, the dying of the Lord Jeſus, and to be crucified to the world by his croſſe, and to do and ſuffer for him, and endeavour the good of others ſouls, and I found my inward man much ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104249:71"/>and ſin weakned. This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God gave me ſome reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but I had not much comfort. This Sacrament, I had ſweet aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that my ſins ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. I kept a faſt day by my ſelf, to ſeek help from God, in the great ſtrait I was in; for no power but his could help me out and deliver me: The Lord did graciouſly aſſiſt me, and afterward I kept a faſt in private with others about it, my heart was out of fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and very he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vy, and perplexed, but God came in and melted, and made the duty very ſweet; and at night, a ſweet, quiet, and believing waiting frame came upon my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; God anſwered my prayer ſweetly and particularly. That text in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. the Lord made good to me. I reſolved to keep a faſt by my ſelf and humble my ſoul before the Lord, and poure out my complaint before him, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104249:72"/>ſeek ſtrength from him; God ſweetly encouraging me with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Scriptures, and melted my heart, oft pouring it into his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and drew me out of my ſelf into Jeſus Chriſt. Again I kept a faſt by my ſelf to ſeek the Lord, and humble my ſelf for my fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and God did ſweetly melt my heart, and helped me to pray, and made it a comfortable day, and I deſire to hope and wait for a gracious anſwer, and God did anſwer me very graciouſly. I kept another faſt by my ſelf, to ſeek the Lord to mortifie my corruptions, that I might not diſhonour him, but be acted by him and his grace, to his glory, and to order all for me aright according to his will; the Lord ſweetly aſſiſted me, and I deſire to wait for an anſwer, and bleſſed be his name, he hath ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered my prayer by many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable providences which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104249:72"/>to improve to his glory. God did viſite me with a fever, and had ſhaken his rod at me before, but I took not warning as I ſhould, for God is ſo gracious, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights not in afflicting the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of men, if they return. Gods chaſtizing me was very full of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gentleneſſe, I felt little or no pain, but kept my bed from mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day till ſaturday, and God chain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up Satan that he did not at all tempt me, but I lay with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace and aſſurance of Gods love, and God made my bed for me, and raiſed me up again in much faithfulneſſe, and ſhewed me why he had contended with me, and I acknowledged Gods dealings exceeding juſt, mercifull, and faithfull. The ſinne that God did eſpecially afflict me for at this time, as he did convince me, was, my great ſinning about the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, God will be ſanctified in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104249:73"/>them that draw nigh to him, and I had been very formal in duties, &amp; cold in them, neglected to go to Ordinances, did not prepare my ſelf before I went as I ſhould; coming ſometimes late, diſtracted at holy duties, and was unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under them, not ſo mourned when I heard Gods name blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, glad when Sabbaths were done, and vain thoughts then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, guilty of much Sabbath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation, in coming to the Lords day with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon worldly frame of heart, and having ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon worldly frame of heart on the ſaid dayes; Being too long in bed on the Lords dayes mornings, and not doing duties as Sabbath dutys, and not walking anſwerable to the Sabbath Ordinances I enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. So that it was high time for God to come now. The experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that I have got by this are, that God is very patient, and good,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104249:73"/>and faithful, he will not leave me unpuniſhed altogether, neither will he fail or forſake me in it, therefore I reſolve in his ſtrength to love him, fear him, and his goodneſſe, ſerve him, walk cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with him, be zealous for him, give up my ſelf &amp; my all to be laid out for his glory, and in his ſervice, and to ſanctifie him in all my drawings near to him, to ſerve him alone, in his ſtrength, and the power and ſpirit of Chriſt ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling me, for if he leave me, to my ſelf, I ſhall ſinne more then ever; theſe are ſome of the fruits I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſhould come forth from this rod. I kept a Faſt by my ſelf to humble my ſoul before God, and renew my repentance, and ſeek help and direction from him, and my God made it a ſweet day unto me. I kept another faſt by my ſelf for the ſame mercies that I did the other before, and the Lord did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104249:74"/>much aſſiſt and help me to mourn for ſinne, and to pray for <hi>Zions</hi> peace, and of the land. I kept ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſt by my ſelf to humble my ſoul for mine own ſins, and the ſins of others, and to ſeek for direction in the ſtraight I was in, and the Lord did help me, and after much and long ſeeking to God, the Lord did anſwer me.</p>
                  <p>The fourteenth of <hi>December,</hi> 1655. God did vouchſafe unto me a very great deliverance, wherein I ſaw abundance of his power, wiſdom, and goodneſſe in it to me, which were wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered, in the way of it, to the Glory of God, and honour of the Goſpel, even to the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it elſewhere, to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hand of God; An anſwer of prayer. I was fully freed and cleared. I deſire this great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhould be food for faith, and that I called on God for, it
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104249:74"/>was the faithfulneſſe of God in performing that promiſe; that he would keep in his way, and he kept me in my calling, which was his way, and ſo I had protection from him, and he found out a way for me, and I deſire to improve my freedome for his glory, and walk more ſpiritually and cloſely all my dayes with God, then ever I have done. The experiences I got by this were,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it is the duty and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Chriſtian to walk and keep in the way of God, had I been out of Gods way, I had been gone.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That there is no difficulty too hard for God, but his wiſdom can find out a way, and his power can bring it to paſſe, and his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe will do it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That it is the duty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to wait Gods leiſure and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104249:75"/>time, which is the beſt and fitteſt time.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is their duty alſo never to truſt to their own heart, but in God, and expect direction, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and guidance from him, and I reſolve in Gods ſtrength al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be and continue in his way, and to believe no difficulty too hard for him, but his wiſdom can find out a way, and when we cannot, his power can bring it to paſſe, and his faithfulneſſe will do it, and I will never truſt mine own heart more but wait on God, truſt in him, and expect all from him, and hang upon him by faith and prayer. I kept another faſt by my ſelf, my God did help me in ſome meaſure: I deſire to lay all my ſacrifices on Chriſt, that precious altar, that I may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and anſwered. I kept another faſt by my ſelf for one of my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, God carried me through the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:104249:75"/>duty with ſome ſweet meltings and incomes, I deſire to wait on him for an anſwer, and to live my prayers, and ſtill to truſt in him, and do duties in faith and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I kept another faſt by my ſelf about my children, deſiring to do all in Chriſts ſtrength, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all upon his account, and God did give me very precious anſwers. I kept another faſt by my ſelf to be humbled for my own and others ſins, as my childrens, my Fathers houſe, and Sir <hi>Walters,</hi> and the ſins of the times, and to ſeek bleſſings and ſanctifications of Gods diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and directions from the Lord, and deſire to wait. I kept another faſt by my ſelf, for my children and other things, God did humble me in ſome meaſure, and aſſiſt me, And God did won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully and ſpeedily anſwer. O bleſſe the God that heareth pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and follow God for further
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104249:76"/>mercie. I kept another faſt by ſelf, about one of my children, and God gave me ſome ſweet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in the duty, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in Chriſt. This Sacrament I received Chriſt and had ſweet fruits from him. This Sacrament God did help me to go againſt ſome difficulties, and my ſpecial errand to Chriſt was to deliver me from vain roving thoughts, and to fill my heart daily with heavenly meditations, and that I may ſtill breath forth ſweet ejaculations, God gave me Chriſt and I deſire to believe and wait. This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I received Chriſt by faith, and deſire to live on him, but my errand was for a broken heart, and ſence of ſinne aright, and I had ſweet meltings. This Sacrament I had ſome hatred of ſinne, and God brought me home with reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions in his ſtrength to honour him, and act for him, in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104249:76"/>where I were going, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all I am and have for his uſe and honour, and to be more meek to them without. This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God freely gave me Chriſt, and all his purchaſe and offices, and as I went for more faith and wiſdome, ſo I came away believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving I ſhould have them; God did aſſiſt me. This Sacrament God gave me Chriſt, and ſent me comfortably home. This Sacrament I received Chriſt according to his promiſe and deſire a Law of thankfulneſſe, ſhould by the hand of the Spirit, and in the bloud of Chriſt, be written in my heart, and a law of obedience in my whole life, and all my converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This Sacrament though I was failing every way, yet God freely gave me Chriſt his body broken, and his precious bloud, the ſeal of the Covenant of Grace; and in the afternoon, God told
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104249:77"/>me out of his word, he would give me a new heart; which was that I went for as one end, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to wait and believe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are what as yet are only come to hand, which Mrs. <hi>Scot</hi> had with her at <hi>Holbourn</hi> where ſhe died, probably ſhe may have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more in the Country whence ſhe newly came.</p>
                  <p>Out of theſe may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſefull Obſervations, for our own Inſtruction, in our going forth by the footſteps of this member of Chriſts flock.</p>
                  <p>As Though <hi>not many wiſe after the fleſh, not many mighty not many noble are called,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26. yet ſome are. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Many of them believed, alſo of honuorable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which were Greeks, and of men, not a few.</hi> Mar. 15.43. <hi>Joſeph an honourable Counceller which alſo waited for the Kingdom of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though vanity be never ſo much
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:104249:77"/>yet grace can overpower all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed,</hi> &amp;c. Titus 3.3. <hi>And we our ſelves were ſometimes fooliſh diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>When we are making our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit to gratify our carnall ſenſes, God can bring us to better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.20. <hi>I was found of them that ſought me not, I was made manifeſt unto them that asked not after me.</hi> The Lord took her at her hunting pleaſures to bring her to the comforts of his own ſpirit.</p>
                  <p>Any meanes when ſanctified, can bring us to the Word, and ſo to God, as the hurting of her leg did her, and the crowing of the Cock did <hi>Peter,</hi> to remember the word Chriſt ſpake, and to return to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.74, 75.</p>
                  <p>The Lord makes ſome great in the world great in grace alſo;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:104249:78"/>rich in earthly bleſſings, rich in ſpiritual likewiſe, that they have all things given them for this life and a better richly to enjoy. <hi>Job</hi> the greateſt of all the men of the Eaſt, <hi>Job</hi> 1.3. <hi>And there was none like him in the earth, a perfect and an upright man one that feared God and eſchewed evil,</hi> verſ. 8.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe workings that come from God, carry all to him againe. She endeavoured to act all for him that had done ſo much for her, the waters that come out of the ſea return thither again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. <hi>Of him, and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>She was brought home the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all way of Gods people, by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of bondage to the Spirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Ye have not rcoeived the ſpirit of bondage again to fear, but ye have received the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:104249:78"/>of Adoption whereby we cry Abba Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Gods grace works irreſiſtably, ſhe would fain have run away from God, he would not let her go, but carried her through, and ſuffered her to have no power to leave ſeeking of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68 18. <hi>Thou haſt aſcended on high, thou haſt led captivity captive, thou haſt received gifts for men, yea, for the rebellious alſo, that the Lord God may dwell among them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such as are moſt caſt down in converſion are uſually moſt lifted up afterward. She had great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of conſcience then, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous pangs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And afterward full aſſurance all her ſins were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by the bloud of Chriſt, and great rejoycings. The Father made merry with the Son when he returned, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.23, 24. that was driven to husks, and ready to periſh, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16, 17. The Jailour
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:104249:79"/>that <hi>came trembling,</hi> Acts 16.29. afterwards rejoyced, <hi>believing in God,</hi> verſ. 34.</p>
                  <p>The way to make our Election in God ſure, is by the work of grace in our ſelves: I know it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, (ſaith ſhe) that God did chuſe me from all eternity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had made me to give up my ſelf to Jeſus Chriſt, for thoſe ends that Jeſus Chriſt gave himſelf for me, 1 Theſ. 1.4, 5. <hi>knowing brethren beloved, your election of God, for our Goſpel came not unto you in word onely, but alſo in power, and in the holy Ghoſt, and in much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> Rom. 8.29. <hi>For whom he did foreknow he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his Son.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some believers are very high and eminent in the workings and waies of God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Your faith groweth exceedingly, and the charity of every one of you all towards
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:104249:79"/>each other aboundeth.</hi> 1 Cor. 1.5. <hi>In every thing ye are enriched by him in all utterance, and in all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>ſo that ye come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in no gift.</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.5. <hi>Our Goſpel came not unto you in word on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but alſo in power, and in much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. <hi>Ye rejoyce with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi> Act. 13.52. <hi>The diſciples were fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with joy and with the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Acts 9.31. <hi>Walking in the fear of the Lord and the in comfort of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Pſ. 32.8. <hi>I will inſtruct thee &amp; teach thee in the way which thou ſhalt go, I will guid thee with mine eye.</hi> Iſa. 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters I will be with thee, and thorow the rivers they ſhall not overflow thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire thou ſhalt not be burnt; neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> Pſal. 46.1. <hi>God is our refuge and ſtrength a very preſent help in time of trouble.</hi> Gen. 22.14. <hi>In the mount of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:104249:80"/>Lord it ſhall be ſeen.</hi> 2 Chron. 17.6. <hi>His heart was lift up in the ways of the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 119.32. <hi>I will run the way of thy commandments, when thou ſhalt enlarge my heart.</hi> Pſal. 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy commandments.</hi> She was a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the higheſt form, a ſtar of the firſt magnitude, one that had not onely the graces of the Spirit, but the ſealings and joyes of the Spirit in abundance, and was rich in the knowledge of the Myſteries of Chriſt. One that the Lord did much councell, and direct in all her waies, and kept her in all her ſtraights, and redeemed her with great deliverances, her extremity often was Gods opportunity. One that was raiſed up and elevated in his ſervice fulfilling all his wils.</p>
                  <p>Great Saints have ſometimes ſore aſſaults from Satan, as ſhe had ſometimes buffetings with <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:104249:80"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. haply leaſt ſhe might have been exalted above meaſure, through the abundance of incomes. Pirats ſet upon the richeſt ſhips, and trees are moſt threſhed that be fulleſt of fruit.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtians high in comforts are low in acts of mortification, and ſelf-denial: How often did ſhe faſt and afflict her ſoul before the Lord, and was ſenſible of her failings, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.37. <hi>She depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not from the Temple, but ſerved God with faſtings and prayers night and day.</hi> In all ſhe did, ſhe went out of her ſelf to the ſtrength of Chriſt, attributing all to him. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.10. <hi>By the grace of God I am what I am, and his grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon me was not in vain, but I laboured more abundantly then they all, yet not I but the grace of God, which was with me.</hi> Gal. 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:104249:81"/>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me and gave himſelf for me.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of whom I am chief.</hi> Trees with high tops have deep roots.</p>
                  <p>Such ſerve God truly, that conſcienciouſly ſerve him ſecretly. Many days of faſts and ſeeking God we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in ſecret by her ſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. <hi>When thou prayeſt enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut the door, pray to thy father which ſeeth in ſecret.</hi> And verſ. 16, 17. <hi>When thou faſteſt be not as the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But ſo,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>as that thou appear not to men to faſt, but unto thy father which is in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a happy thing to be rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them that are truly godly. How did ſhe pray for her husband and children? Nature helps grace, and grace acts for nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.2,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:104249:81"/>3. <hi>I have great heavineſſe and continuall ſorrow in my heart, and I could wiſh that my ſelf were accurſed from Chriſt, for my brethren my kinſmen according to the fleſh.</hi> Rom. 10.1. <hi>Brethren my hearts deſire and prayer to God for Iſrael is, that they may be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When we cannot ſerve God ſo well as we ought, we ſhould ſerve him as well as we can, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit duties. She was troubled for being ſo unprepared, yet came to Sacraments and found God very graciouſly. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18. &amp;c. <hi>The good Lord pardon every one that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth his heart to ſeek God, the Lord God of his fathers, though he be not cleanſed according to the purification of the Sanctuary, and the Lord hearkened to Hezekiah, an healed the people.</hi> Cant. 6.12. &amp;c. <hi>I went down into the garden of nuts to ſee the fruits of the valley, and to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the vine flouriſhed, and the pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granates
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:104249:82"/>budded, or ever I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, my ſoul made me like the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots of Aminadab.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is good to come to God in Ordinances for particular mercies. She made this and that her ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all errands, and the Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed them unto her, <hi>Job</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt alſo decree a thing and it ſhall be eſtabliſhed unto thee.</hi> Pſal. 37.4. <hi>Delight thy ſelf alſo in the Lord and he ſhall give thee the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of thy heart.</hi> Mat. 21.22. <hi>and all things whatſoever ye ſhall ask in prayer believing, ye ſhall receive.</hi> 1 Sam. 1.27. <hi>For this child I pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and the Lord hath given me my petition which I asked of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God oft cometh in ſeaſonably to them that wait upon him in Ordinances, as frequently to her in hearing, with ſuitable and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable words, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.20, 21. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee thy teachers, and thine ears ſhall hear a word behind
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:104249:82"/>thee, ſaying, this is the way walk ye in it, when ye turn to the right hand and when ye turn to the left.</hi> Prov. 8.34. <hi>Bleſſed is the man that heareth me, watching daily at my gates, waiting at the poſts of my doors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Great enjoyments of God in Ordinances, ſhould not take us from them, or make us live above them, but carry us the more to God in and by them. Thus it was with her, the more ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the more ſhe waited upon God in them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.2. <hi>To ſee thy power and thy beauty as I have ſeen thee in the Sanctuary.</hi> 2 Chron. 30.23. <hi>And the whole Aſſembly took councell to keep other ſeven days, and they kept other ſeven days with gladneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sacraments are not only ſealing, but exhibiting Ordinances, of more grace and comfort to belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, ſhe received much encreaſe from God in and by them. <hi>Mat.</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:104249:83"/>3.16. <hi>And Jeſus when he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ized, went up ſtraightway out of the water: and lo, the heavens were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened unto him, and the Spirit of God deſcended like a dove, and light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> upon him.</hi> Acts 8.39. <hi>The Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> after Baptiſme went away rejoycing.</hi> The bread and wine which are the ſignes in the Lords Supper, are nouriſhing.</p>
                  <p>The incomes from God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are very various, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one, ſometimes another, ſometimes more, and ſometimes leſſe, ſometimes ſooner, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times later, ſometimes ſhe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> meltings at the Sacraments, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reſolutions to ſerve God againſt ſin, giving up her ſelf to the Lord; ſometimes meekning of her ſpirit, ſometimes deſires to come again, ſometimes great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance and comforts, ſometime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> at the time, ſometimes afterward 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Who then is P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:104249:83"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd who is Apollo? but Miniſters by whom ye believed, even as the Lord gave to every man. I have planted, Apollo watered, but God g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve the increaſe.</hi> Iſa. 56.7. <hi>I will make them joyfull in my houſe of prayer.</hi> Act. 10.44. <hi>While Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter yet ſpake theſe words, the holy Ghoſt fell on all them which heard the word.</hi> 2 Chron. 1.6. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon offered a thouſand burnt offerings</hi> verſ. 7. <hi>In that night did God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto Solomon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When we have performed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Lord, we are to expect his anſwers. She would wait for returns, when ſhe had been a ſeeking of him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>I will direct my prayer to thee and will look up.</hi> Pſal. 85.8. <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſpeak.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lord ſometimes withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from Ordinances, that we ſhould not reſt in them but in himſelf. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. <hi>We had the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:104249:84"/>ſentence of death in our ſelves, that we ſhould not truſt in our ſelves, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> God which raiſed the dead.</hi> This uſe ſhe made thereof when ſhe had not altogether theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes.</p>
                  <p>A gracious heart is as mindful of mercys received to return praiſes and anſwerable walkings to God, as to pray for mercies wanted. <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.14. <hi>And the Lord ſaid to Moſes, write this for a memoriall in a book.</hi> Pſal. 103.2. <hi>Bleſſe the Lord, O my ſoul, and forget not all his benefits.</hi> Pſal. 116.12. <hi>&amp;c. What ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits towards me, I will take the cup of ſalvation, and call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the name of the Lord, I will pay my vowes unto the Lord now, in the preſence of all the people.</hi> Thus did ſhe note down in a Book the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious dealings of God towards her to quicken her to thankfulneſs and ſuitable improvements to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:104249:84"/>
                  <p>Temptations and buffetings are not to be given way unto, but oppoſed, to conquer them; Her faith (ſhe ſaid) fought with them, and they were ſubdued under her. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Reſiſt the devil and he will flee from you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Afflictions and mercies when improved bring forth much fruit in the people of God, as her ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deliverances did in her. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.11. <hi>Now no chaſtening for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous, but grievous, nevertheleſſe after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word it yeeldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſſe, unto them which are exerciſed thereby.</hi> Pſal. 32.7. <hi>Thou art my hiding place, thou ſhalt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me from trouble: thou ſhalt compaſſe me about with ſongs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Gods gracious returns of prayer to his people, do much engage them in affection to him, and encourage them for the future to ſeek more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:104249:85"/>them. O bleſſe the God (ſaith ſhe, that heareth prayers, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God for further mercies. And elſewhere, I deſire this great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhould be food for faith. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1, 2. <hi>I love the Lord, becauſe he hath heard my voice, and my ſupplications, becauſe he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined his ear unto me, therefore will I call upon him as long as I live</hi> 2 Cor. 1.10. <hi>Who delivered us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver: In whom we truſt that he will yet deliver us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>True grace is permanent and growing, the motion that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall is perpetuall. My God (ſaith ſhe) doth give me ſweet experience of the growth of grace in my ſoul: The longer ſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the more ſhe acted, <hi>Job</hi> 17.9. <hi>The righteous alſo ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger.</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:104249:85"/>Revelations 2.19. <hi>I know thy works, and charity, and ſervice, and faith, and thy patience, and thy works, and the laſt to be more then the firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:104249:86"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Thorowgood's</hi> Letter to Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Underſtand you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to print your Sermon preached at the funeral of our moſt honored friend Mrs. <hi>Scot,</hi> that Saint of the Lord, that eminent believer of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt form, and therewith ſome nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative concerning her. It is not onely lawfull, but ſometimes very
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:104249:86"/>expedient to ſhew the Coates and Garments <hi>Dorcas</hi> made whilſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; eſpecially the excellencies of great believers whoſe memory is bleſſed; and which may ſo much conduce to the advancing of the glory of Gods free grace, and the good of others; for which cauſe no doubt the ſeverall graces and holy actings of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are left on holy record. I am willing to caſt my mite into the treaſury. Her converſion (ſhe told me) was occaſioned by a fall from her horſe in hunting time, whereby one of her legs were put out of joynt, which the Lord ſo ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to her, as it brought her to the ſerious receiving of the immortall ſeed of the Word thereby forming Chriſt in her, in whom the New-birth did moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently ſhine ever after. O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py fall, that did ſo exalt her; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was very vain, delighting
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:104249:87"/>in dancing and hunting; But then God brought her to hear his rod, and to receive inſtruction, and to ſolace her ſelf in the joys of the spirit, and to purſue the ways of holineſſe; thus God did not take away her comforts, but chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them, and gave her better in the room; He did not dry up the ſtream, but diveried it and turned it into a better channel. It was not long after her converſion from nature unto grace, but ſhe was likely to be perverced from truth unto error, and was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about the way of Separation, ſome of which way lived near her, and got acceſſe to her, and ſo was in danger of looſing on the one ſide, much of what ſhe had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the other; But the gracious God, out of his continuing good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, (as ſhe told me) proviced Mr. <hi>Elmeſtone,</hi> that old diſciple, a skilfull Pilot to freer her coune
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:104249:87"/>again to rights, who can relate more concerning this particular; and ever ſince through grace, hath ſhe ſailed with a full and ſteady gale in the ways of truth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and hath been a fired ſtar, in the Church of God, no ways moved with the ermurs, and fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of many round about her, wandring on the right hand and on the left; after once God had cauſed her eares to hear that word behind her, ſaying, <hi>This is the way walk in it,</hi> ſhe ſhunned their books, company and diſcourſes tending that way, as taking no pleaſure therein, and would not tempt God, by going to the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſuch as cauſed diviſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſully perſwaded of the truth and way ſhe practiſed; thus trees by ſhaking become more firmely stoted. She was converted in the height of Prelacy, and was of the true old Puritane and right Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt's
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:104249:88"/>Spirit unto her dying day, accounting our Churches and Miniſtery eſſentially true, though wanting in circumſtantials, ſhe earneſtly deſired, and in her place fervently endeavoured a through reformation, without forſaking the Aſſemblies, and leaving the work to others, but would ſet to her helping hand alſo. She went on to perfection, but laid not again foundations; ſhe held what was good, rejecting the ill, being of quick and ſound underſtanding to diſcern between good and bad; She would mourn with the houſe of <hi>Cloe,</hi> for what was beyond her ſphere to amend, and walked very comfortably with Chriſt her ſelf in the middeſt of the golden Candleſticks, having her own gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments undeſiled, and others un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe did no way prejudice her. She was a very great and conſtant prizer of the faithfull
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:104249:88"/>Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced not in their light for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhe knew them that were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her in the Lord, and eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them very highly in love for their works-ſake, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed peace and unity with the reſt. <hi>She walked in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> never miſſing any when able to go, and much troubled when neceſſarily detained by illneſſe; ſhe thought not they could be too often enjoyed, when ſhe could not go in her Coach in Winter time, by reaſon of the deepneſſe of the way between <hi>Congherſt</hi> and the Church, ſhe would walk on foot in all the rainy and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous weather, that long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous up and down hill way: (to ride ſhe alwayes dreaded ſince her fall) and when in <hi>London,</hi> often did ſhe go from high <hi>Holbourn</hi> to <hi>Chriſts</hi>-Church to the morning
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:104249:89"/>Sermons on the Lords dayes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reft began, and then to them afterwards. Conſtantly did ſhe attend Lectures and Faſts publick and privare. In Summer when ſhe was at <hi>Congherſt,</hi> uſually there in the Countrey, ſhe had a weekly Lecture at <hi>Howkherſt,</hi> and the Miniſters ſtill at her houſe. Very often did ſhe keep in ſecret whole dayes of faſting and ſeeking God by her ſelf in prayer, and humbling and afflicting her ſoul before the Lord. When I was forth ſhe her ſelf would pray with her family; once I coming home late, unknown to her, heard her, and ſhe prayed to my very great admiration and ſatisfaction. Twice in the family morning and even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not onely prayers were, but ſomething of the word, and ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of a Pſalm: On the Lords day at noon, ſinging and praying with the family, beſides morning
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:104249:89"/>duries, and evening reperitions of the Sermons, together with ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Pſalm, and Praying. A true ſanctifier and ſpirituall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of the Lords dayes ſhe was, and dared not to ſpeak of any worldly civil (though at other times lawful) things, and oft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed the too much liberty many profeſſors take on thoſe days, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing their conſciences were ſo benummed concerning that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment more than others, that they could talk of ſuch civil and worldly things then without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, not conſidering that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is broken in words &amp; thoughts as well as others, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when that place in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. is ſo expreſſe againſt it, <hi>Not doing thine own wayes, nor finding thine own pleaſure, nor SPEAK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING THINE OWNE WORDS, viz.</hi> upon the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath dayes. Beſides her privare
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:104249:90"/>duties in the family, ſhe was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in ſecret duties by her ſelf, daily her uſuall manner was (as I have been certainly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) In the mornings as ſoon as ſhe was up to go into her cloſet a little while by her ſelf, and then went to the performing of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duties together with the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; after they were done, then ſhe retired into her chamber by her ſelf, and read the Bible in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, reading and meditating about one hour, and then went into her cloſet afterwards a pretry while. Before ſupper ſhe uſed to go into her chamber and cloſet ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent time, yea though late, when ſhe was neceſſarily detained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad before ſhe came home; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter duties performed in the family at nights, when the reſt were gone to bed, ſhe would walk about half an hour meditating in her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and reaſoning out any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:104249:90"/>that was upon her ſpirit, to find out the cauſe thereof, and to remove it; ſaying, ſo her heart was brought into frame again, and not before; Then ſhe went into her cloſet about three quarters of an hour, and this every day. She never went abroad but ſhe went firſt into her cloſet for ſome while to prayer, and ſo ſhe did again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her returnings home. On the Lords days at noon after duty done in the family, ſhe would retire by herſelf, til they went to the publick worſhip againe; upon the week dayes ſhe would much complaine ſhe was ſo ſtraitned for time, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring more to ſpeed in ſecret by her ſelf. She was a be lever that had not onely the graces of the Spirit, but the ſealings and the joyes of the Spirit in her; She had much aſſurance, even to the riches of it; She knew ſhe was of God, and Chriſt was her Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:104249:91"/>having loved her and given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for her, and that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, with all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and mercies therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and Ordinances were hers; And therefore in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where Providence caſt her, would ſhe partake of all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and not infringe her Chriſtian right and liberty, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tied to one particulat place, or people onely, living without the Sacrament till ſhe came there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; though ordinarily ſhe looked upon her ſelf as a member of that Church where her uſuall dwelling was. She was filled with joy, and walked in the comforts of the holy Ghoſt, ſhe was of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry chearfull Spirit, and grace did carry it on very graciouſly and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually; ſhe had much communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God in all the means of grace, the Lord made her joyfull in the duties of prayer, the Word
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:104249:91"/>was the ſavour of life unto life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, and the rejoycing of her heart. Exceeding incomes ſhe had at the Table of the Lord, there ſhe ſat under Chriſts ſhadow with great delight, and his banner over her was love, and his fruit was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſweet unto her taſte; whilſt the King ſat at his table with her, her ſpiknard did uſually ſend forth the ſmell thereof. The Lord did grearly bleſſe that Ordinance of his Supper unto her; ſhe ſaid ſhe could ferch from the Lord there, any mercy ſhe wanted, direction in ſtraights, ſupport and comfort in diſturbances, power againſt ſin and Satan, grace to carry her on in the wayes of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Much refreſhing ſhe had in ſinging of Pſalms, ſhe had many and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular returns of prayers from God, which ſhe much looked up to him for, after ſhe had directed them unto him, and took ſpeciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:104249:92"/>of his gracious anſwers, and improved them with thankfulneſs to his glory. She was of very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent naturall parts, full of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and prudence; as appeared alſo in the well managing of her many and weighty affaires, and did greatly abound in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Divine Myſteries, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Scriptures; Much weaned from and crucified to the world; Whilſt her Father Sir <hi>Mathew Howland,</hi> &amp; her Unkle Sir <hi>John Howland</hi> lived, ſhe would ſay (foreſeeing the ſame, as being their onely heir) ſhe was afraid of too much of the world coming to her. Never any uſe or increaſe would ſhe take for any money's ſhe lent, though to a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſumme and time; and left under her own hand, that her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould take none alſo for the ſame after her, in caſe ſhe died before the principall was paid in.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:104249:92"/>Her good works and charity not only <hi>Hawkherſt,</hi> but <hi>Holburn</hi> alſo, and other parts can teſtifie, as your ſelf well know, and can am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply relate. Her good works ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not only to her own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo to the Hungarian Scholers, who come ſo far to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of our practicall Divinity, counting her ſelf a Member of the ſame univerſal Body with them. For divers years, often would ſhe have one of them time after time with her, whilſt in the Countrey; and now did take care of one this Winter, at one of her ſons, till next Summer ſhe thought to come again, and retake him into her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: Their Land, have divers already returned into it, that have cauſed her piety and liberality to ſound amongſt them there. She diſdained not to viſit any of her pooreſt neighbours, and did love to do it, to raiſe up pity in her to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:104249:93"/>wards them, and thankfulneſſe to God for her ſelf, who had made the difference: Neither did ſhe refuſe to do the meaneſt offices of love for the good of them and theirs. Her artire, your ſelf knowes, how grave and modeſt it was; as alſo her Daughters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out nakedneſſe, or unſeemlineſſe. The gracions Providences of God were exceeding many, and very great and remarkable towards her; wherein ſhe ſaw much of her Fathers care and goodneſſe, which ſhe took ſpecial notice of, and was abundantly thankful for, and endeavoured to improve them anſwerably to his Glory, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in her Diary, where ſhe hath kept an account of them, and alſo of her waies towards her God, as there ſhe often calls him. She was like that vertuous woman your Text ſpake of, in her carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages in and toward her Family,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:104249:93"/>ordering and taking care thereof, and them in it; and herſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about ſomething or other of the ſame, when ſhe was not in her ſpirituall converſes with the Lord, or taken off by other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. She conſidered well both her husbands eſtates, and freed them from the incumberances for her children, whom, ſhe much endeavoured to make the children of God, in bringing them up in his nurture and admonition, and keeping divers days of faſts by her ſelf, to ſeek the Lord for them, in which and divers other reſpects, they could not but ariſe and call her bleſſed, and give we her of the fruit of her hands and let her own work praiſe her in the gates. As her life, ſo her death was full of grace and comfort, the Lord ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened her upon her bed of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing; and made all her bed in her ſickneſſe; when ſhe was
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:104249:94"/>walking through the valley, of death ſhe feared no evil, her God was with her, his rod and his ſtaffe they comforted her, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred to her an enterance abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. Though her paines and tortures were great (the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians applying cupping glaſſes to her, and lancing her) yet the Lord did comfortably lift up the light of his countenance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and put gladneſſe in her heart, and made her patience have its perfect work, ſhe was full of heaven, breaking forth in expreſſions of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to her, ſaying, God hath been very good to me, how good is God, and how good it is to wait upon God, there hath not the leaſt cloud interpoſed between God and my ſoul all this ſickneſſe, I will go to my God triumphing.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:104249:94"/>Thus with gladneſſe and rejoycing was ſhe carried to enter into the Kings Pallace, into the joy of her Lord, where there is fullneſſe of it, and pleaſures for evermore. O mark we the perfect, behold we the upright, for the end of ſuch is peace. No marvail that even <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> in the ſence hereof, did ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to die the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and that his end might be like theirs; and well had he done if he had withall deſired his life alike. For ever magnified be my good God, who hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of our habitations, that cauſed the lines to fall unto me in ſuch a pleaſant place, ſo long even ſix years in the ſame family with her, and that I ſhould be choſen and ordained a Paſtor to her and the people there at <hi>Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt;</hi> That ever I was ſo acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch an eminent, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:104249:95"/>experimentall, ſpiritual, ſtaid believer, abounding ſo much with the graces, and ſealings, and joyes of the holy Ghoſt; That I ſhould have ſuch a taſte of that happineſſe and delight that is in the ſociety of reall Saints; How did I live as in a lower heaven, walking as in Paradiſe, whilſt I was there, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in the goodneſſe of the Lord all the day long, calling the wals ſalvation, and the gates praiſe; what ſweet experiences of Chriſt had I frequently communicated to me from her! How greatly did ſhe ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>engthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my hands in the Lords work in the middeſt of all the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition among that people; the righteous God recompence it, and all the work and labour of love, ſhe ſhewed towards his name unto me, into the boſome of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> children ſeven fold, as likewiſe al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I found from my much honoured long deceaſed friend Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> husband, in his day, whoſe memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:104249:95"/>is very precious to me. O unhappy Engagement, that ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engaged us from one another, and that people there: The Lord is righteous, and his wayes alſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth, his pathes are judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a God of truth and without iniquity, juſt and right, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in counſel, excellent in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Wiſdome and might are his, he changeth time; and ſeaſons making every thing beautifull in them; manifold are his works, in wiſdome hath he made and done them all, the earth is full of his rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, whatſoever he pleaſeth that doth he in heaven, and in the earth, and in all deep places. We are not to murmure and ſay, what is the cauſe the former dayes were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then theſe, for we may not wiſely inquire concerning this; yet unſenſible we ſhould not be of ſuch a loſſe, and breach as this is, like the ſea, who can heal it?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:104249:96"/>whereunto ſhall I liken and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it? that ſuch a burning and ſhining light ſhould go out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, ſuch a fixed ſtar, a ſtar of the firſt magnitude, ſhould ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our horizon: How hath the Lord covered thoſe parts with a cloud in his anger, and caſt down the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them to the ground? how is the gold become dimme, and the moſt fine gold changed! how is the precious daughter of <hi>Zion,</hi> and the glory of thoſe parts departed! For theſe things I weep, mine eye mine eye runneth down with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Oh that my head were wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and mine eyes a fountain of teares, that I might weep day and night, even with the weeping of <hi>Jazer,</hi> yea mourn with a great mourning, as the mourning of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dadrimmon</hi> in the valley of <hi>Megid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> for good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> when he was taken away. <hi>Oh dolor exprome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, non ſum ſolito contentus ſone,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:104249:96"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> indociles lugere ſimus, Scotam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>emus.</hi> Ye Miniſters of Chriſt, weep over her, that was ſuch a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall conſtant prizer of you. O Weal of <hi>Kent,</hi> take up a wailing for her, the brighteſt ſtar in all your firmament is ſet. O <hi>Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt,</hi> make a bitter lamentation for her, whoſe coming among you, was like the rain upon the mown graſſe, as ſhoures that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the earth. O poor of thoſe parts, and <hi>Houlbourn,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſet upon the ground and keep ſilence, caſt duſt upon your heads, gird your ſelves with ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, hang down your heads to the ground, ariſe cry out in the right, in the beginning of the watches, pour out your hearts like water before the face of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ift up your hands towards him, who hath taken her away from you, that did not with hold you from your deſire, nor cauſed your
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:104249:97"/>eyes to fail, that did not eat her morſel herſelf alone, and you did not eat thereof; that did not ſee you without covering, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for want of clothing: whom your eares have bleſſed, when heard her, and your eyes have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven witneſſe to her, when ſeen her, and your loines have rejoyced when warmed by her; and ye wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows whoſe hearts ſhe hath made to ſing for joy, when ſhe ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as Queen among the mourners. O <hi>Hungarian</hi> Scholars, call for the mourning women, and ſend for cunning women, that they may come, and let them make haſte and take up a wailing for you, that your eyes may run down with teares, end your eye lids guſh out with water, for a great Patroneſſe of yours is gone. Sir I am not yet out of my amazement by this great and ſuddain blow, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the end of the Lord. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:104249:97"/>of her ſelf, it is happineſſe, not ſuffering her to be longer abſent from him here in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, having with her ſwift mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion finiſhed her courſe ſo ſoon. But why in reſpect of us, is this Citizen of heaven ſo ſoon gone from us? when but ſomewhat more then in the midſt of her dayes? We may fear a ſtorm coming, when the Father cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his Children ſo haſtily home; The Lord fit us for the worſt of times, and our laſt hour. When Mr. <hi>Scot</hi> her husband, that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfull Magiſtrate died, and ſoon after, that godly and faithfuull Miniſter of Chriſt, in the neighbouring place of <hi>Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt,</hi> alſo died, it was much upon my heart that ſome evill was a coming, and accordingly was I greatly carried out to preach among my people on <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 57.1. <hi>The righteous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:104249:98"/>and no man laieth it to heart, and mercifull men are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, none conſidering they are taken away from the evill to come.</hi> And that Lords day it was finiſhed, that very week was that great riſing in <hi>Kent,</hi> in 1648. though I had not the leaſt hint thereof till they were up, which God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed notwithſtanding in mercy preſently to avert. But this is not yet participated, the Lord goeth by me, and I ſee him not, he paſſeth on alſo, and I perceive him not; his way is in the ſea, and his path in the great waters, and his footſteps are not known. Theſe wheeles within the wheeles are not yet manifeſted; the great thing upon my ſpirit is, Lord, why haſt thou taken away thy faithfull and tallent-improving ſervant, whilſt nature was ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:104249:98"/>ſtrong and vigorous in her, thus before her time? Righteous art thou O LORD, when I plead with thee, yet let me talk with thee of thy judgments. We cannot ſee thy works from the beginning to the end; yet muſt we believe, though clouds and darkneſſe are round about thee, yet righteouſneſſe and judgement are the habitation of thy throne. I know O Lord, thy judgements are right, and thou in faithfullneſſe haſt afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us: Thy works are great, ſought out of all them that have pleaſure therein, thy ſecret is with them that fear thee; thy way O GOD is in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and there are thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be ſeen. The good Lord ſanctifie this great and ſore affliction to us, and hereby the more quicken us to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of our time and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:104249:99"/>to the utermoſt, whilſt it is day, before our night come, when we alſo ſhall ceaſe to work. So prayeth, Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours, affectionatly to ſerve you in Chriſt.</hi> NICOLAS THOROWGOOD. <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſometime at</hi> Hawkherſt, <hi>now at</hi> Monkton <hi>in the Iſle of</hi> Thanet <hi>and County of</hi> Kent.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:104249:99"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Elmſtones</hi> Letter to Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am perſwaded that not onely we the friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of this lately deceaſ'd Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman Mrs. <hi>Scot,</hi> the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon of Piety and Chriſtian wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but even ſtrangers that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before heard of her, yea thoſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:104249:100"/>of the generation to come will con you much thanks, for that your labour, you intend (as by a Letter from Mr. <hi>Thorowgood</hi> I underſtand) to hold up her remembrance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the living, though ſhe be dead, that the glory of Gods grace (which was in her eminently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous) may thereby be magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and ſhe ſet forth as a lively pattern of piety, by Chriſtian Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen to be imitated. It will indeed conduce nothing to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of her happy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who without ſence of what is here done below touching her, to her full ſatisfaction enjoyeth the beatificall viſion of her moſt dear Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. But it were pitty, that ſuch a mirrour of Gods grace in her, and the ſplendor of it ſhining from her, ſhould lie in obſcurity, the knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of might cauſe many thankſgivings to God for her, and happily kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:104249:100"/>in ſome breſt a kindly flame of a godly imitation of her wayes. Touching the occaſion of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion what it was, I perceive that Mr. <hi>Thorowgood</hi> hath informed you, which I think he could do better than my ſelf, as who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a good while in her family, might hear her often relate it, ſo that touching that I need to ſay nothing, ſave only that ſo it was, as he writeth, occaſioned by a fall from a horſe, and the putting of her leg out of joynt. The danger whereof put her upon the reading of Books that concerned piety and Religion, whereby it pleaſed the Lord to work in her ſome ſerious ſence and care of Religion. But ſhe did no ſooner begin to mind matters of Religion, but that ſome two of that way of the rigid ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration called <hi>Browniſme,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>John Turner,</hi> the name of one of which was <hi>Scotchford,</hi> both
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:104249:101"/>living in <hi>Cranebrook;</hi> by the means of a Tenant unto <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Gate-houſe took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, and together got acceſſe to her, and began to inſtill into her ſome of their principles of the ſeparation, and it ſeems had much ſhaken her, ſo that ſhe began to be ſcrupulous of holding commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with our then Churches, <hi>viz. England.</hi> It fell out that while they were thus working at times upon her, and ſhe wavering, that in that Feſtivall time of Chriſts Nativity, which in ſuch houſes was kept with ſome ſolemnity of good cheer theſe Sectaries came to <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> and after dinner had gotten an opportunity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with Mrs. <hi>Scot,</hi> then Mrs. <hi>Roberts,</hi> ſomewhat privately in a Chamber, where yet was preſent Mrs. <hi>Criſp</hi> her Aunt, a godly Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, now alſo deceaſed, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:104249:101"/>
                  <hi>John Morgan</hi> a retainer to that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, a very honeſt man, now alſo dead; The good Gentlewoman, &amp; the reſt were ſomewhat puzzeled, with the ſomewhat knottydiſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe Sectaries: Now it was ſo by Gods Providence, that I was alſo at that time, and had been there for ſome dayes, invited by Sir <hi>Walter Roberts,</hi> now deceaſed to, and his Son, young Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> who, for ſix years together, at leaſt, had been my Scholar, and boarded in my houſe; Wereupon it came into that <hi>John Morgans</hi> mind, to make a motion to Mrs. <hi>Roberts</hi> to ſend for me, and that I ſhould conferre with thoſe Sectaries, ſhe did gladly entertain the motion, and they how willingly, I know not, yeelded to it, ſo I coming to them, there we conferred toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſome two houres (it may be) before them, about points of Separation, eſpecially about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:104249:102"/>the Sacrament amongſt ſuch a confuſed multitude, as then was the manner, by the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the times, whether it might lawfully be done, or could be done with any comfort. The iſſue of our conference was ſuch by the Lords bleſſing, that Mrs. <hi>Roberts</hi> was ſatisfied about ſuch objections as they made, had her ſcruples cleared, liſtened no more to their ſuggeſtions, and they being now out of hope of gaining her, left her, ſo that from thence, ſhe continued her atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the publick Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and held in, in the Communion of our Churches as true, though then in many things ſomewhat corrupt and defective. And this, Sir, is the ſtory of that paſſage, if you think meet to make uſe of it, I ſhould be willing that you would not mention me by name, but only
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:104249:102"/>ſay that a Miniſter being at that time there by Providence, was called in to conferre with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, and did ſatisfie Mrs. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts.</hi> I cannot tell whether a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage or two be much worth the mentioning, but now I am wtiting I have a mind to adde them. Firſt while Mrs. <hi>Roberts</hi> was as a ſo jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> ſummer ended, when they could not walk abroad before ſupper, in the evenings when it began to be too dark to ſee how to work, and it was too early to light a candle, it was her cuſtome with her Aunt Mrs. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and ſome other young Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the houſe, Mrs. <hi>Criſp</hi> her daughters eſpecially, to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſome one of their cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and ſit talking together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an hour or ſo, till candels were lighted. Their talk it may be was ſometimes of civil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſuch accidents as had
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:104249:103"/>fallen out, and come to their hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but there was alſo ever for the moſt part, ſomewhat of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in relating what they had read in ſome good book or other, or what they had ſometime heard. I once upon an occaſion about ſuch a time ſtayed at <hi>Glaſſenbury</hi> one whole night, and then they called me into their meeting and conference, where they requeſted me to repeat the heads of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon I had preached abroad not long before, about ſetting up Idols in the heart, out of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the 14. and to pray with them. Next, when the keeping of the houſe was put over by his Father to Sir <hi>Walter Roberts</hi> his Lady, who being weak in her intellectuals, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to manage the buſineſſe of the houſe, Mrs. <hi>Roberts</hi> then was fain to be governeſſe of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and overſee the ways thereof, which was pretty great; In this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:104249:103"/>time ſhe was in ſome ſtraight how to perform her morning duty of cloſet prayer to the Lord, ſhe thought that it was meeteſt that God ſhould be firſt ſerved, and ſought unto, for his bleſſing all the day after; But it ſeemeth that the thoughts of houſhold buſineſſe did interpoſe, that ſhe performed it not with meet freedom of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: wherefore Mr. <hi>Whitfield</hi> that faithful Miniſter of the Lord, who had ſome relation to the family by his wife, coming there ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted her doubt to him; who gave her his opinion, that it was the ſafeſt way for her firſt to go down and ſettle things in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily for the forenoon buſineſſe, and then to retire her ſelf to her ſolitary devotion, which ſhe might attend with all freedome of Spirit from houſhold affaires, and without fear of interruption: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if upon her giving the firſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:104249:104"/>place to her devotion, if mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the family had at any time done amiſſe, it might have turned to ſome reproach of her religious profeſſion, as making her negligent in that her domeſticall employment. So ſir after much ſcribling I have done, if any thing written will be worth the inſerting in your intended Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, I ſhall be glad of it, that I have lighted on any thing to celebrate the memory of that gracious Gentlewoman, whoſe loſſe I ſhall feel with others, for want of that encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we had from her in piety, and her reſpect of us, and ſo deſire to lament it; If not, it is enough, that I have ſhewed my weak deſire to contribute ſomewhat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward her Funerall Obſequies; and ſo commending you to the ſafe keeping and love of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:104249:104"/>our good God in Chriſt, I reſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <date>Jan. 31. 1658.</date>
                  <signed>Yours in the ſincerity of Chriſtian reſpect, and good affection; <hi>JOHN ELMESTONE.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:104249:105"/>
               <head>Mr. <hi>Elliſton's</hi> Letter to Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Worthily honoured and dearly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Friend.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am requeſted to give in my thoughts and experiences of that pious and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Saint Mrs. <hi>Scot,</hi> once ſhining in our eyes, but now alas extinct, the fragrancy of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:104249:105"/>whoſe piety was as an oyntment poured forth among us. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I have delaied it, and had thoughts wholly to have waved it, not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but fearing I might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from her worth, or eclipſe it, and being alſo conſcious to my ſelf of my unworthineſs and unfitneſs to give teſtimony eſpecially of ſo eminent a ſervant of Chriſt, who alas ſo oft doubt of mine own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. This femal glory bleſſed among women, whom God had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed with the oyl of Grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove moſt of her fellowes, was an inſatiable worſhipper of God in Chriſt (as was ſaid of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) much on the wings of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly contemplation and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was this divine Eagle. She had laid up her treaſure there, no marvaile then her heart had its tendency thither, ah precious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome wherein was lodged ſo much of heaven. Oh how fearful (good
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:104249:106"/>ſoul) was ſhe that the lean kine ſhould eat up the fat, that <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>'s part ſhould play the thief to <hi>Mary</hi>'s. Oh how watchful over her heart, calling it ſlippery and deceitfull, ſaying ſhe had but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while to keep it, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward would pay for her paines urging her ſelf on that ground to a fidelity and conſtancy in her watch and ward. She carried <hi>Mary</hi>'s Alabaſter of precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with her, which ſhe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to open and pour out plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on others, ſuting her ſavoury diſcourſe according to the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the parties ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe withall. Oh how cautious was ſhe of giving any offence in her attire, or any other wayes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe never put on her beſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire but ſhe had thoughts of cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing her ſelf with the rich robe of Chriſts righteouſneſſe, and decking her ſelf with the jewels
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:104249:106"/>of his graces. Oh how exact in all her walkings, carefull to make ſtraight ſteps to her feet, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where ſhe ſhould ſet her foot before ſhe took it up, that ſhe might tread ſafely, ſhe was rich in Grace, but poor in Spirit, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Grace lodged in a low heart. Poor worthleſſe creature, was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in her mouth. She would condeſcend to converſe familiarly with the pooreſt member of Chriſt not having the grace of Chriſt in reſpect of perſons, the ointment of her love fell as well upon the skirts of the garment as on the head; ſhe loved Grace for it ſelf, looking on it as amiable clad in ruſſet, as in velvet, in a poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, as well as in her Miſtreſſe. As all her delight was in the Saints, ſo her delight was in all the Saints, ſhe had a heart truly mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to the world, ſhewed in her
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:104249:107"/>contemptuous ſpeeches of it, and the glory thereof. Oh, how beautifull were the feet of Godly Miniſters to her, a rare grace in theſe dayes. How afraid of the corruptions of the times, of ſoul poyſoning Doctrines, ceaſing her ſelf, and perſwading others to ceaſe from harkening to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that cauſeth to erre from the words of knowledge. She was a great lover of the Word, of the Sabboths, very carefull as that her ſelf, ſo thoſe under her charge ſhould carefully prepare for them before they came, ſo holily to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it when it was come; A great prizer of all Gods Ordinances, and of all opportunities of Grace, which ſhe did husband to the great improvement of ſoul good. The obſervation of humbling days was frequent with her, wherein ſhe was very ſolemn, according
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:104249:107"/>to the nature of the duty, and now ſhe reapes abundantly the fruit of her labour. She had a marvelous ſtomack and ſpirituall appetite to the Lords Supper, for the which ſhe did ſolemnly prepare her ſelf, plentifully ſequeſtring her ſelf from the affaires of the world, that ſhe might clean her heart for the acceptable entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of her beloved, no queſtion ſhe met with many a precious dole there, who had ſuch a deſire to be there. She came down from that mount, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> with a ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing face, a heart moſt warm and lively, ſpeeches ſavoury and raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, refreſht with the comfortable ſenſe and feeling of Chriſts love, ſweeter then wine, filled, ſatisfied with marrow and fatneſſe; Chriſt did frequently then and there ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf to her, kiſſe her, therefore her lips dropped honey,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:104249:108"/>as I my ſelf have experience of it, I bleſſe God for it; Bleſſed God what a mercy I am deprived of! Oh ſhe was altogether and alwaies lovely. Her grace added much more worth to her then her birth, or any other accompliſhment ſhe had; much grace there was in her grace, it looked like it ſelf in her. I never was in her company but I went off with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to me, or the fault was my own, I might have learned humility, contempt of the world, to be lively and ſpirituall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Oh what a pittifull heart had ſhe to the poor, eſpecially of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith, and as ſhe had a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart, ſo a bountifull hand, as ſhe ſaw occaſion, and would oft ſay, God lent it her for that end, and it was a great mercy to have a heart to it; to lay out for God, is to lay up for our ſelves;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:104249:108"/>'twas her holy ambition to ſerve God in her generation. She was very ſpirituall in her affections to her relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to her dear Lady Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Children, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully troubled at their deviations, and to think that any that come from her ſhould hiſſe or ſting at Gods glory, oh that thoſe cares, prayers, teares, fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods bottle, when worldly teares drop beſides it, might not (as to any of them) be rendred fruitleſſe. Sir, many of theſe flowers ſhe had growing in the garden of her heart, her veſſel was weak, her grace ſound and ſtrong, ſhe had embarked in her thoſe excellencies that would neither ſink nor ſuffer ſhipwrack. She was rich towards God, here ſhe had a Chriſt for grace, and now ſhe hath him and heaven
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:104249:109"/>with him for glory. She was a <hi>Sarah</hi> for courage, an <hi>Abigail</hi> for wiſdome, a <hi>Mary</hi> for choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the good part, a <hi>Dorcas</hi> for good works, an <hi>Elizabeth</hi> for walking in all the commandments and ordinances of God blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Sir, if ever I had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the happy eſtate of any that ever I was acquainted with, it is greatned in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to her. All that I can ſay is abundantly below her; my prayer to God is, that God would favour me with the favour that he beared to vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Miſtreſſe <hi>Scot;</hi> So ſhall I be viſited I know with his ſalvation. Sir, I hope you will pardon my defects, when you underſtand I was neceſſitated to write this week or not at all, in great haſte having much other work on my hands;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:104249:109"/>the reſt is the ſubſcribing my ſelf, Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Sandhurſt, <date>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 28. 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your younger brother in Chriſt, and unworthy fellow labourer in the Lords vineyard, <hi>PETER ELISTON.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:104249:110"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Another Letter of</hi> Mr. THOROWGOODS. to Mr. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince my laſt to you I received further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation from a friend, concerning that uſeful and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Gentlewoman Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth Scot,</hi> by way of Narrative, of ſome other remarkable paſſages, which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:104249:110"/>were not mentioned in my Letter, which may be worthy imitation, and of ſingular uſe to Chriſtians in theſe declining dayes, and may tend to the magnifying the glory of Gods free grace, ſhining forth in her converſation; in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">I. She was much in holy religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Worſhip and ſervice of God in pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ick, exceeding careful not to loſe any publick opportunity for the good of her ſoul, making all or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inary occaſions of her own and viſits of friends give place, and not to hinder her waiting on God in the publick Miniſtry of his Word. If there were a Lecture ſhe uſed to go unto, and perſons of quality came to viſit her, after ſhe had been with them a while, and time was to go, ſhe would look upon it as no incivility to leave them with the Lady her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:104249:111"/>unleſſe they would go with her. I never knew any ordinary viſit or viſiters detain her from attending the Word of God preached, for almoſt theſe nine years which I have lived in her houſe. She was willing to keep fair Correſpondency with all her friends, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to maintain a moral principle of love, where there was no more; but exceeding tired with Lady's diſcourſe at their viſits, though I ſuppoſe in her preſence it was farre better then otherwiſe. If any buſineſſe unknown fell out when ſhe was going to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, unleſſe it would certainly prove prejudicial to her, ſhe would make it ſtand back and wait till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward: and this I have frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known; and ſhe often ſaid, ſhe found Satan very buſie to hinder her from laying hold of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, this I believe the whole family can teſtifie with my ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:104249:111"/>
               <p n="2">II. As ſhe was carefull not to omit any publick opportunity, ſo alſo as carefull of private duties, ſhe would be ſure not to loſe her cloſet time, where ſhe was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and long, even when others were at their reſt; I lying in the Chamber over her, have often heard her up at one of the clock in the night or rather morning. The Church hath a great loſſe of her prayers, many a petition did ſhe put up in her cloſet, and flouds of tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> did ſhe pour forth, inſomuch that her eyes have been ſore for ſome days together (which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were very well) when any calamity hath been upon the Church of God, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured by any nearly related to her, her teares have been ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that I have behold ſurrowes on her cheeks, and ſo likewiſe upon faſting dayes, ſhe was ſo con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſcious in keeping her cloſet-time,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:104249:112"/>that all her ordinary buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did ſtay till ſhe had done; and when any of her family have gone to her cloſet door, and told her ſome would ſpeak with her, or came to viſit her; If the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were petty, or onely viſitors, let them have been who they would, ſhe would ſtay out her time, knowing the Lady her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was below to entertain them; but if the buſineſſe were of great importance, then ſhe would come; But, to be ſure make haſte to her cloſet again. O the ſweetneſſe ſhe found in her cloſet communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! that ſhe would ſpend ſo much time there in the forenoons, as that ſcarce ſhe had time to dreſs her ſelf; often ſaying, her dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing time was the worſt time of all her time; often bidding her maid make haſte, ſaying, why are you ſo long, I hate to ſpend ſo much time in dreſſing for this is loſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:104249:112"/>time; and whilſt her maid was dreſſing her, ſhe would be mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Letters, or winding up her watch, or ſome imployment or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not induring to ſtand idle any time in the leaſt meaſure, though it were but a very little time; She would not (ſhe ſaid) for a great deal ſpend ſo much time in dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as many do, knowing how to ſpend her time if ſhe had more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſaying, I like this faſhion well either in her apparrell or dreſſing, that ſooneſt could be put on, and take up leaſt time; often charging her maid, to get all things ready againſt ſhe came to be dreſſed, ſaying ſhe could hardly afford her ſelf time to be dreſſed; yea in the winter evenings would ſhe be long in her cloſet. She was a diligent reader of the Scripture privately by her ſelf every day. She kept many dayes of faſts ſecretly by her ſelf upon many occaſions, and for
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:104249:113"/>her children: And thoſe dayes would ſhe ſet apart for the ſaid faſts, upon which there were ſome great ſhews or ſights to be ſeen in the City, as twice ſhe did upon a Lord Mayors day, the occaſion of her faſts falling out on thoſe times of the year, making choice of thoſe dayes rather then others, becauſe of the vanity of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and prophanneſſe in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by ſurfeiting and drunkenneſſe more then at other times; And how full of heaven would ſhe come out of her faſts; How hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly would ſhe pray in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily thoſe nights! How fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how broken hearted in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions! How heavenlized was ſhe! in ſo much that the next day ſhe hath wiſhed, ſhe could live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eating or ſleeping, to ſpend that time upon the immediate ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, ſuch enjoyments of him did ſhe find therein.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:104249:113"/>
               <p n="3">III. As ſhe was much in holy duties publick and private, ſo ſhe was exceeding carefull to perform every duty in its ſeaſon, that one ſhould not juſtle out another, her private performances, ſhould not hinder her publick attendances; and her publick ſervice ſhould not infringe her private, and very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſhe was, in not omitting the leaſt duty. God did give her that ſpirituall art of redeeming and improving time, above thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Chriſtians: Her pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick performances though many, did not abate her one minute of her private.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. As ſhe was carefull in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming all thoſe duties that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned her ſelf, ſo alſo thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her family, reſolving with <hi>Joſhua,</hi> that ſhe and hers would ſerve the Lord. As ſoon as her children came to any underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:104249:114"/>ſhe made them learn the Catechiſmes, firſt Mr. <hi>Wilſons,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bal's</hi> Catechiſmes, and from the year 1653. the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies leſſer Catechiſme, and God did ſo bleſſe her endeavours, that when her children were very young, yet could they ſoon give her an account of their whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme without book; and as ſoon as any of them could read, ſhe cauſed them diligently to read and would exerciſe their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by calling them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what they could remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that they had read in the Bible or other good Books, and of what they had heard when they had been at Church; and it was wonderful to hear what a large ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they would give of what they remembred: Surely God did much bleſſe her prayers for them, elſe I know not how poſſibly they could do ſo: She would make all
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:104249:114"/>children pray privately by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before they went to bed, and in the mornings when they did riſe. Alſo ſhe would inſtruct in repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of what they could remember, what had bin preach'd, telling them oft they muſt give account to God of their time, and what they had read and heard, exhorting them to walk in the waies of God, when ſhe ſhould not be; by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before them the good to be found in Gods ſervice, and the miſeries that would fall on them if they walked not in his waies, She would not keep any ſervant that was prophanely wicked, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe would not have ſuch, if they would give her their ſervice: ſhe would have no ſervant of an erroneous opinion; I have heard her ſeverall times ſay, ſhe would rather have thoſe, that were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane then ſuch, becauſe there is little hope of convincing the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:104249:115"/>but more hope to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the prophane: ſhe was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willing her ſervants ſhould go to Lectures and to the faſts, at the end of the morning exerciſes which were once a moneth; ſhe would afford them time, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them to go to them, and if ſhe had a ſervant that could not read, ſhe would cauſe her children to teach ſuch, and her ſelf alſo would do it as ſhe could ſpare time to encourage them, and buy books for them.</p>
               <p n="5">V. I ſhall give an account of the method of her duties, and every dayes work. Firſt, in the morning as ſhe did riſe, before ſhe was off her bed, ſhe made her children give her an account at her beds ſide, of their Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes in courſe, one, one morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and another another, when they were ſo large in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:104249:115"/>as ſhe could hear but one a time; when ſhe was off her bed, ſhe went to her cloſet for ſome time, then afterward ſhe had refreſhed her ſelf with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſhe would perform fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily duties with the family, when ſhe had no Chaplaine, in reading ſomething of the Word, and prayer; Then ſhe would uſe ſome little exerciſe ſhe could find beſt for her health, which ſhould not be long, and ſo to her cloſet again, reading the Scripture by herſelf, and ſpending the reſt of the forenoon, unleſſe ſome great occaſions called her off till about eleven a clock, when ſhe came out, and while ſhe was making up her own bed (which ſhe did every day, except the Lords days, for her exerciſe) ſhe would cauſe her children to read the Scriptures, one one morning, and another another, and as they read ſhe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:104249:116"/>would ask them, what they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by ſuch a place, inſtructing them as they read; if a place where ſome judgements were denounced againſt ſin or a ſinner, ſhe would ſay, ſee what cauſe you have not to ſin, and what you muſt look for if you do ſo, exhorting them from every ſuch place. By that time ſhe had done and was dreſſed it was well nigh dinner time; in the winter time, ſhe loved not to come out of her chamber before dinner was at table, becauſe the forenoons were ſo ſhort, unleſſe ſome buſineſſe more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry had called her away. In ſummer time, ſometimes ſhe would walk a little before dinner in <hi>Lincolns-Inne</hi>-fields, and twenty to one if ſhe had not found an object of charity to ſcatter her benevolence upon, before ſhe came in again: after dinner, after ſome little ſpace, to her cloſet again, where
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:104249:116"/>ſhe was ſometimes longer and ſometimes ſhorter as her oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions would permit; if that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon ſhe went to a Lecture, or to viſit friends, ſhe would be ſure to go into her cloſet before ſhe went out of doors, and when ſhe came home to her cloſet again for ſome time; then when ſhe was undreſſed and in her night garments, that was the time of her meditation, when ſhe would walk ſometimes an hour, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it drew neer to ſuppertime, and ſo to her cloſet againe till ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was ready, after ſupper, ſhe would walk again till the ſervants had ſupped, and then called them in to family duties together with ſinging of a Pſalm; after the ſame were ended, and ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed ſometime with the Lady her Mother, ſhe would go to her chamber, where ſhe would walk for ſome time, and ſo to her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:104249:117"/>where then ſhe ſpent much time, ſo long as at the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt it would be one of the clock before ſhe went to bed; often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times would ſhe be up till one of the clock in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and manytimes the Belman would cry in the ſtreets, two a clock in the morning, and ſhe no more then a bed, and not a ſleep, asking her maid, if that were the Belman. I verily believe there was no ſhop, keeper more diligent in keeping his ſhop, then ſhe her cloſet; O what a trade did ſhe drive for heaven! ſhe was one that made Religion her buſineſſe indeed. Upon the Lords dayes, ſhe would be up ſomewhat earlier then on other dayes, though later up on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday nights; and if in <hi>London,</hi> in the ſummertime, ſhe would go to the morning Sermons at ſeven of the clock, if the weather were good, and then to the reſt; She
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:104249:117"/>was full of heaven in all her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes on the Lords dayes, ſhe was one as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. that did turn away her foot from the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, from doing her pleaſure on Gods holy day, and called the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honourable, honouring him, not doing her own waies, not finding her own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking her own words; all her diſcourſe at table dinner and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and every where thoſe dayes, ſhould be heavenly, and ſpeaking of what was taught thoſe dayes, not a word would come from her unſuitable to the day. I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve if one had been ſet to watch her all thoſe days long, he ſhould not have trapp'd her in one word unſuitable to the day; if any thing had diſpleaſed her, ſhe would not have been diſpleaſed on thoſe dayes. On Lords-dayes-nights when ſhe was come from Church,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:104249:118"/>and undreſſing her ſelf, her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren gave her an account of what they had heard at Church, and what ſuch had read, as ſtay'd at home and could not go; and thoſe of her children ſhe could not hear then, ſhe would call to account while the ſervants were at ſupper, and afterward the family to duty, and repeated amongſt them what ſhe had written at Church thoſe dayes; This laſt year ſhe cauſed her eldeſt daughter Mrs. <hi>Frances Scot,</hi> to repeat in the family, being able alſo to write; After repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Pſalm they ſung and then ſhe her ſelf prayed; in which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as ſhe was heavenly, ſo longer then other nights; the Lord did not onely give her the grace and ſpirit of prayer, but alſo a great gift in prayer: And as ſhe was one of great gifts and parts, ſo very humble, her parts did no way puff her up or cauſe her to go out of her
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:104249:118"/>ſphere in the leaſt, one of her Chaplaines did much urge her in the Country (where ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly had one in her houſe) to hear her pray, but at no hand would ſhe do it, this by the way: After duty done in the family, ſhe went againe to her chamber, and ſo to her cloſet, &amp; would be there ſomewhat longer then other nights and take her bed-time the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day mornings, indeed it would be morning, before ſhe went to bed. Her uſuall Lecture dayes at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> every week, were Tueſday's at <hi>Clements,</hi> Wedneſdays Mr. <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> at <hi>Black-Friars,</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, and if ſhe could have time in the afternoon Mr. <hi>Calamy's</hi> at <hi>Aldermanbury;</hi> before Mr. <hi>Jenk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins</hi> Lecture was at <hi>Black-Friars,</hi> ſhe was conſtantly at <hi>Aldermanbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> Thurſdayes at <hi>Dunſtones</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> to hear Mr. <hi>Manton,</hi> or at Mr. <hi>Caſe's</hi> Lecture at <hi>Martines</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:104249:119"/>in the fields, and Saturdayes at <hi>Gregories</hi> in the afternoons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the morning exerciſes when they were neer.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. As ſhe did lay out her ſelf and time in the ſervice of God, ſo alſo the greateſt part of her eſtate, laying up little here; her layings out, were more then her layings up: ſhe was heaping up her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in heaven, where neither moth nor ruſt conſume, nor thief break through and ſteal, how did ſhe ſcatter her benevolence every day! and ſo as her left hand knew not what her right hand did. Much money did ſhe caſt into the poors baſon at Faſts, and at thoſe faſts once a moneth at the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exerciſe, the keeping of which ſhe omitted not, though many times not well; at other private faſts ſhe gave very much; there was ſeldome a week in the winter
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:104249:119"/>time, but ſhe was called to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate faſt for particular perſons in ſome great affliction, many weeks ſhe hath bin known to have been twice a week at thoſe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dutys, to the performance of which ſhe would be ſure to make all ordinary buſineſſes and viſits of friends give place; ſome weeks it hath bin known ſhe hath bin at 3 faſts a week, at which faſts ſhe gave the more, knowing it would be given to the godly poor, and being winter time, and the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with them; which ſcatterings would ariſe to no ſmall ſumme in a year if they could be known how much they were. Sometimes it hath bin obſerved and ſometimes could not, at the leaſt it hath been obſerved to have bin 2 ſhillings a time; at the more private faſts ſhe would give more: In her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe faſts, if ſhe thought the farneſs of the way would weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:104249:120"/>her ſtrength, which ſhe kept for the dutys, ſhe would ſend for a Coach; at nights if fair, ſhe would often come home on foot, both for her healths ſake, and to give the more to the poor; ſaying many might think, ſhe went on foot out of covetouſneſſe, but they would be much miſtaken; and when ſhe came home from thoſe faſts, what ſhift would ſhe make to ſteal up to her chamber by the door of the room, where ſuch as came to viſit, were, that ſhe might not be detained from her cloſet duty's. But to return to her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity every day, how did ſhe ſcatter her bounty among the poor! not to ſuch as made a trade of begging, though they uſed never ſo moving expreſſions, knowing they were prophane, and would take no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther courſe of life, from ſuch ſhe would receive many a hard word, when they ſaw her give to others
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:104249:120"/>and not to them, and her ſervant hath been fain to defend her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from their affronting her, by not giving her way enough to paſſe. Now as ſhe walked <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ſtreets, ſhe would carefully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, if ſhe could ſee any poor old people, whom ſhe would call to her, or command her ſervant to go and call them to her; and would ask them if they were very poor, and if they were care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſerve God, and did go to Church, and what hopes they had to be ſaved, to which they would anſwer as they were able, and ſome would ſay, I bleſſe God Miſtreſſe I am not ſo poor, but the Lord doth provide for me, that I am not driven to beg, nor extreamly want, to whom ſhe would then give; if ſhe had been in haſt, and gone by any poor people, and ſaw they did not beg ſhe would ſend her ſervant ſometimes with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:104249:121"/>to them, whilſt ſhe kept on her way: She would not walk <hi>London</hi> ſtreets long but one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would come to her begging for an almes, and ſhe would ask her ſervant if he knew them to be common beggers, if he thought no, ſhe would be ſure to give. At Lectures, if ſhe ſaw any that were old or in poor habit attending the word, then ſhe would be ſure to give them. In cold ſeaſons when it was hard with poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhe would be alwaies a ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſufferings of the poor, that had no fire, or ſcarce any bread, much ſympathizing with them, asking her ſervant if he knew any that it went hard with, that ſhe might relieve them, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her benevolence: her charity was ſo well known, that ſeldome a day, if at home, but ſhe had petitions from one or other for the ſame, many under the notion
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:104249:121"/>of diſtreſſed Miniſters, becauſe they knew they ſhould receive the greater almes, and that they might be ſure not to miſſe of the ſame, they would get a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall of their godly lives, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and neceſſitys, with the names of ſome godly Miniſters, ſhe knew or had heard of, and then hath ſhe given the more, when ſhe thought their condition real, but give it ſo privately her ſelf, as none ſhould know how much but the receivers. None that came with petitions did go away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out almes, unleſſe ſhe had known they had come the ſecond time, having bin relieved before: many a time have her ſervants gone up to her chamber, or when ſhe was at dinner, with a paper or petition (they knowing when beſt to find her at home) ſhe would ask them if they knew them fit objects of charity, but let the anſwer be I
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:104249:122"/>or no, ſhe would ſend them down ſomething if ſhe could not go down her ſelf, ſaying, ſhe would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give to them that had no need, then ſend one empty away that had; ſending them down word, if they had counterfeited other mens names, they would very much wrong themſelves (as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we could perceive they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed her charity, and grew ſo ſubtile, that they would indite Letters punctually to her by name, they having their almes according to their demerit.) Her charity was exceeding much amongſt all the poor people at <hi>Hawkherſt</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> where her houſe was, where ſhe was many ſummers ſince ſhe uſed to be in <hi>London</hi> the winters, they have all cauſe to remember how many have had relief at her door; Seldom a Lords day but eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen had relief there, ſhe would exhort thoſe poor to ſerve God,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:104249:122"/>and ask them if they had been at Church thoſe dayes, and if they had not they ſhould have nothing; which cauſed ſome of them to go the oftner, for they would be ſure to tell one of another, and not a day in the week, but many of them came and had relief at noon and at nights. Sir, more I could relate but Mr. <hi>Caſe</hi> ſpake of them in his Sermon, and therefore ſhall proceed no further in theſe particulars, wherein alſo it may be well ſaid, She exceeded many daughters that have done virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
               <p>It pleaſed the Lord to fill her concluding days with many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and abundance of buſineſſe, it was wonderfull the trouble and the many buſineſſes ſhe had, and how chearfully ſhe went through them, and how eminently the Lord appeared to be with her in carrying her through all, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:104249:123"/>whatſoever ſhe took in hand to proſper. Since ſhe came out of the country laſt, ſhe ſcarce had any time to viſit her friends, this winter which I never knew before, but ſpending her time much with God. Indeed her life was a continual mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion never idle in the leaſt, either in her cloſet, or with her family in performing religious dutys, or reading, or writing, or going to Lectures and faſts, or giving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions concerning houſhold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, ſhe being now houſe-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in <hi>London</hi> alſo as well as in the Countrey, to eaſe the Lady her Mother in her ancient years, which ſhe did never before in <hi>London,</hi> though alwaies in the Countrey, till this laſt winter.</p>
               <p>O what a loſſe hath her friends, yea what a loſſe hath the Church of God, and hundreds of poor people, whoſe bowels ſhe refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; But now ſhe is gone before,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:104249:123"/>where her ſoul long deſired to be. The Lord help us to make after, and not to wiſh for her again or that ſhe had not dyed. Why ſhould we be ſo fooliſh, it will not avail; and why ſo ſinfull and ſo impudent, as to contradict God, he ſaw it beſt to remove her hence, and why ſhould we wiſh her back again, ſhe is triumphing in heaven over the world, ſinne and Satan, ſinging Alleluja unto Him that ſitteth on the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever. She is among the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of holy angels, and with the great God the judge of all, and with the bleſſed Jeſus the Mediator of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and with the holy Ghoſt the Comforter, in the large fruition of the beatificall viſion, where is fulneſſe of joy and pleaſures for evermore, and why ſhould I wiſh
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:104249:124"/>her from ſuch glorious company, and tranſcendent bliſſe, as never eye hath ſeen, nor ear heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath entered into the heart of man; to which mercy's the Lord in his due time bring us by the merits of his dear Son and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir,</hi> Theſe ſix Heads which I have here ſent you, are what my friend writ, who hath known her many years.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, affectionately to ſerve you in Chriſt, <hi>NICOLAS THOROWGOOD.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 79. lin. 19. for <hi>Landherſt,</hi> r. <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt.</hi> p. 118. l. 12. dele <hi>comma</hi> after <hi>ſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:104249:124"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
